<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Indian Constitution</string>
    <string name="action_settings">Settings</string>
    <string name="title_activity_preamble">Preamble</string>
    <string name="title_activity_parts">Parts</string>
    <string name="title_activity_schedules">Schedules</string>
    <string name="title_activity_amendments">Amendments</string>
    <string name="title_activity_scrolling">Indian Constitution</string>


    <string name="Preamble">
        <b>WE, THE PEOPLE OF INDIA,</b> having solemnly resolved to constitute India into a <b>SOVEREIGN SOCIALIST SECULAR DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC</b>[1] and to secure to all its citizens:\n\n
        <b>JUSTICE,</b> social, economic and political;\n\n
        <b>LIBERTY</b> of thought , expression, belief, faith and worship;\n\n
        <b>EQUALITY</b> of status and of opportunity; and to promote among them all\n\n
        <b>FRATERNITY</b> assuring the dignity of the individual and the unity and integrity of the Nation[2];\n\n
        <b>IN OUR CONSTITUENT ASSEMBLY</b> this twenty-sixth day of November, 1949, do <b>HEREBY ADOPT, ENACT AND GIVE TO OURSELVES THIS CONSTITUTION.</b>\n\n
        [1]<i>Subs. by the Constitution (Forty-second Amendment) Act,1976,s. 2, for "SOVEREIGN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC" (w.e.f. 3-1-1977</i>\n
        [2] <i>Subs. by s. 2, ibid., for "unity of the nation" (w.e.f. 3-1-1977).</i>
    </string>

    <string name="part1"><b>Part 1 (Art. 1 to 4)</b>\n The Union and its Territories</string>
    <string name="part2"><b>Part 2 (Art. 5 to 11)</b>\n Citizenship</string>
    <string name="part3"><b>Part 3 (Art. 12 to 35)</b>\n Fundamental Rights</string>
    <string name="part4"><b>Part 4 (Art. 36 to 51)</b>\n Directive Principles of State Policy</string>
    <string name="part4A"><b>Part 4A (Art. 51A)</b>\n Fundamental Duties</string>
    <string name="part5"><b>Part 5 (Art. 52 to 151)</b>\n The Union</string>
    <string name="part6"><b>Part 6 (Art. 152 to 237)</b>\n The States</string>
    <string name="part7"><b>Part 7 (Repealed)</b>\n The States in Part B of First Schedule</string>
    <string name="part8"><b>Part 8 (Art. 239 to 242)</b>\n The Union Territories</string>
    <string name="part9"><b>Part 9 (Art. 243 to 243O)</b>\n The Panchayats</string>
    <string name="part9A"><b>Part 9A (Art. 243P to 243ZG)</b>\n The Municipalities</string>
    <string name="part9B"><b>Part 9B (Art. 243ZH to 243ZT)</b>\n The Co-Operative Societies</string>
    <string name="part10"><b>Part 10 (Art. 244 to 244A)</b>\n The Schedules and Tribal Areas</string>
    <string name="part11"><b>Part 11 (Art. 245 to 263)</b>\n Relations between the Union and the States</string>
    <string name="part12"><b>Part 12 (Art. 264 to 300A)</b>\n Finance, Property, Contracts and Suits</string>
    <string name="part13"><b>Part 13 (Art. 301 to 307)</b>\n Trade, Commerce and Intercourse within the territory of India</string>
    <string name="part14"><b>Part 14 (Art. 308 to 323)</b>\n Services Under the Union and the States</string>
    <string name="part14A"><b>Part 14A (Art. 323A to 323B)</b>\n Tribunals</string>
    <string name="part15"><b>Part 15 (Art. 324 to 329A)</b>\n Elections</string>
    <string name="part16"><b>Part 16 (Art. 330 to 342)</b>\n Special provisions relating to certain classes</string>
    <string name="part17"><b>Part 17 (Art. 343 to 351)</b>\n Official Language</string>
    <string name="part18"><b>Part 18 (Art. 352 to 360)</b>\n Emergency Provisions</string>
    <string name="part19"><b>Part 19 (Art. 361 to 367)</b>\n Miscellaneous</string>
    <string name="part20"><b>Part 20 (Art. 368)</b>\n Amendment of the Constitution</string>
    <string name="part21"><b>Part 21 (Art. 369 to 392)</b>\n Temporary, Transitional and Special Provisions</string>
    <string name="part22"><b>Part 22 (Art. 393 to 395)</b>\n Short Title, Commencement, Authoritativre Text in Hindi and Repeals</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part1">Part 1</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part2">Part 2</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part3">Part 3</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part4">Part 4</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part5">Part 4A</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part6">Part 5</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part7">Part 6</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part8">Part 7</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part9">Part 8</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part10">Part 9</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part11">Part 9A</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part12">Part 9B</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part13">Part 10</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part14">Part 11</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part15">Part 12</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part16">Part 13</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part17">Part 14</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part18">Part 14A</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part19">Part 15</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part20">Part 16</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part21">Part 17</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part22">Part 18</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part23">Part 19</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part24">Part 20</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part25">Part 21</string>
    <string name="title_activity_part26">Part 22</string>
    <string name="large_text">
 "Material is the metaphor.\n\n"

        "A material metaphor is the unifying theory of a rationalized space and a system of motion."
        "The material is grounded in tactile reality, inspired by the study of paper and ink, yet "
        "technologically advanced and open to imagination and magic.\n"
        "Surfaces and edges of the material provide visual cues that are grounded in reality. The "
        "use of familiar tactile attributes helps users quickly understand affordances. Yet the "
        "flexibility of the material creates new affordances that supercede those in the physical "
        "world, without breaking the rules of physics.\n"
        "The fundamentals of light, surface, and movement are key to conveying how objects move, "
        "interact, and exist in space and in relation to each other. Realistic lighting shows "
        "seams, divides space, and indicates moving parts.\n\n"

        "Bold, graphic, intentional.\n\n"

        "The foundational elements of print based design typography, grids, space, scale, color, "
        "and use of imagery guide visual treatments. These elements do far more than please the "
        "eye. They create hierarchy, meaning, and focus. Deliberate color choices, edge to edge "
        "imagery, large scale typography, and intentional white space create a bold and graphic "
        "interface that immerse the user in the experience.\n"
        "An emphasis on user actions makes core functionality immediately apparent and provides "
        "waypoints for the user.\n\n"

        "Motion provides meaning.\n\n"

        "Motion respects and reinforces the user as the prime mover. Primary user actions are "
        "inflection points that initiate motion, transforming the whole design.\n"
        "All action takes place in a single environment. Objects are presented to the user without "
        "breaking the continuity of experience even as they transform and reorganize.\n"
        "Motion is meaningful and appropriate, serving to focus attention and maintain continuity. "
        "Feedback is subtle yet clear. Transitions are efﬁcient yet coherent.\n\n"

        "3D world.\n\n"

        "The material environment is a 3D space, which means all objects have x, y, and z "
        "dimensions. The z-axis is perpendicularly aligned to the plane of the display, with the "
        "positive z-axis extending towards the viewer. Every sheet of material occupies a single "
        "position along the z-axis and has a standard 1dp thickness.\n"
        "On the web, the z-axis is used for layering and not for perspective. The 3D world is "
        "emulated by manipulating the y-axis.\n\n"

        "Light and shadow.\n\n"

        "Within the material environment, virtual lights illuminate the scene. Key lights create "
        "directional shadows, while ambient light creates soft shadows from all angles.\n"
        "Shadows in the material environment are cast by these two light sources. In Android "
        "development, shadows occur when light sources are blocked by sheets of material at "
        "various positions along the z-axis. On the web, shadows are depicted by manipulating the "
        "y-axis only. The following example shows the card with a height of 6dp.\n\n"

        "Resting elevation.\n\n"

        "All material objects, regardless of size, have a resting elevation, or default elevation "
        "that does not change. If an object changes elevation, it should return to its resting "
        "elevation as soon as possible.\n\n"

        "Component elevations.\n\n"

        "The resting elevation for a component type is consistent across apps (e.g., FAB elevation "
        "does not vary from 6dp in one app to 16dp in another app).\n"
        "Components may have different resting elevations across platforms, depending on the depth "
        "of the environment (e.g., TV has a greater depth than mobile or desktop).\n\n"

        "Responsive elevation and dynamic elevation offsets.\n\n"

        "Some component types have responsive elevation, meaning they change elevation in response "
        "to user input (e.g., normal, focused, and pressed) or system events. These elevation "
        "changes are consistently implemented using dynamic elevation offsets.\n"
        "Dynamic elevation offsets are the goal elevation that a component moves towards, relative "
        "to the component’s resting state. They ensure that elevation changes are consistent "
        "across actions and component types. For example, all components that lift on press have "
        "the same elevation change relative to their resting elevation.\n"
        "Once the input event is completed or cancelled, the component will return to its resting "
        "elevation.\n\n"

        "Avoiding elevation interference.\n\n"

        "Components with responsive elevations may encounter other components as they move between "
        "their resting elevations and dynamic elevation offsets. Because material cannot pass "
        "through other material, components avoid interfering with one another any number of ways, "
        "whether on a per component basis or using the entire app layout.\n"
        "On a component level, components can move or be removed before they cause interference. "
        "For example, a floating action button (FAB) can disappear or move off screen before a "
        "user picks up a card, or it can move if a snackbar appears.\n"
        "On the layout level, design your app layout to minimize opportunities for interference. "
        "For example, position the FAB to one side of stream of a cards so the FAB won’t interfere "
        "when a user tries to pick up one of cards.\n\n"
    </string>

    <string name="firstamendment">
    <b>First Amendment</b> \n\n
    In June 1951, the Constitution (First Amendment) Act was passed, and the following Amendment in the Constitution were inserted : (i) To Article 15, a new clause (4) was added: (ii) clauses (2) and (6) of Article 19 were recast; (iii) After Article 31, Article 31A and 31B were inserted; (iv) For original Article 85, a new Article was substituted; (v) In Article 87, clauses (1) and (2) were recast; (vi) For the original Article 174, a new Article was substituted; (vii) In Article 176, clauses (1) and (2) were recast: (viii) Clause (1) of Article 341 was recast; and similarly, clause\n\n
    (1) of Article 342, sub-clause (a) of Article 342, sub clause (a) of clause (3) of Article 372, and clause (1) of Article 376 were also recast; (ix) After the Eighth Schedule to the Constitution a Ninth Schedule was added and thirteen laws passed by State Legislatures were included in it so that those Acts might not be challenged in courts.\n\n
    The main purpose of the Amendment was the removal of certain practical difficulties created by court decisions in several cases such as Kameshwar Singh vs. State of Bihar, Romesh Thapar vs. State of Madras, Brij Bhusan vs. State of Delhi and Motilal vs. Government of Uttar Pradesh. The issues involved in these cases were numerous, such as the scope of the fundamental right of freedom of speech, acquisition of Zamindari (land) of intermediaries, conflict between a citizen’s fundamental right to practise any profession, or to carry on any business or trade (Article 19) and State monopoly of any trade, and so on.
</string>
    <string name="secondamendment">
    <b>Second Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Second Amendment, amended Article 81 in order to remove the prescribed limit of 7,50,000 of the population for one member to be elected to the Lok Sabha. According to the original provision, at least one member was to be elected to the Lok Sabha for every 7,50,000 of the population. It was further provided that the maximum number of elected member to the Lok Sabha should not exceed 500.
</string>
    <string name="thirdamendment">
    <b>Third Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Third Amendment brought about changes in the Seventh Schedule consisting of the three Legislative Lists and entry 33 of the Concurrent List was substituted by a new one.
</string>
<string name="fourthamendment">
<b>Fourth Amendment</b> \n\n
    Article 31 and 31A were amended by the Constitution Fourth Amendment Act. Clause (2) of Article 31 clause (1) of Article 31A were substituted by new clauses. As a result of these, the adequacy of the quantum of compensation paid for the compulsory acquisition of property for ‘a public purpose’ could not be questioned in a court of law. It also amended Article 305 and the Ninth Schedule.
    </string>
<string name="fifthamendment">
<b>Fifth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Constitution (Fifth Amendment) Act amended Article 3. In the Constitution there was no time limit during which a State Legislature should express its boundaries, which the Centre may like to make. With the help of this amendment, it was provided that the State will be required to express its views on such matters within such period as may be specified in the reference or within such further period, as the President may allow.
    </string>
<string name="sixthamendment">
<b>Sixth Amendment</b> \n\n
    In this Act, the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution was amended and in the Union List, a new entry was added after Entry 92 in the State List, a new Entry was substituted for Entry 54. It also amended Articles 269 and 286 dealing with inter-state Sales-tax.
    </string>
<string name="seventhamendment">
<b>Seventh Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Seventh Amendment brought about the most comprehensive changes so far in the Constitution. This amendment was designed to implement the State Reorganisation Act. The Second and Seventh schedules were substantially amended for the purpose of the States Reorganization Act.
    </string>
<string name="eighthamendment">
<b>Eighth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Act extended the period of reservation seats in Lok Sabha and State Legislatures for the Anglo-Indians, the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes by another 10 years.
</string>
<string name="ninthamendment">
<b>Ninth Amendment</b> \n\n
    It provided for the transfer of certain territories of India to Pakistan under an agreement between India and Pakistan as a part of a comprehensive settlement of border disputes between the two countries.
    </string>
<string name="tenthamendment">
<b>Tenth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Tenth Amendment integrates the areas of Free Dadra and Nagar Haveli with the Union of India and provides for their administration under the regulation making powers of the President.
    </string>
<string name="eleventhamendment">
<b>Eleventh Amendment</b> \n\n
    It amended Article 71 so as to make it clear that the election of the President or the Vice President shall not be challenged on the ground of any vacancy for whatever reason in the appropriate electoral college. It also obviates the necessity of a joint meeting of the two Houses of Parliament (Article 66) by constituting them into an electoral college for the election of the VicePresident.
    </string>
<string name="twelfthamendment">
<b>Twelfth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The main object of the Amendment was to add Union Territories of Goa, Daman and Diu to the Union of India and for this First Schedule of the Constitution was amended.
    </string>
<string name="thirteenthamendment">
<b>Thirteenth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Act provides the creation of Nagaland as the Sixteenth State of the Union. The Amendment provides also for the vesting of certain special responsibilities in the Governor of Nagaland.
    </string>
<string name="fourteenthamendment">
<b>Fourteenth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The amendment provides for the incorporation of the former French Establishments in India, under the name Pondicherry, as an integral part of the territory of the Indian Union. It also amended Article 31 to increase, from a maximum 20 to 25, the number of seats assigned in the Lok Sabha for the Union Territories.
    </string>
<string name="fifteenthamendment">
<b>Fifteenth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The amendment raised the retirement age of High Court Judges from 60 to 62 years. It also empowered the various High Courts to hear cases against the Union Government.
    </string>
<string name="sixteenthamendment">
<b>Sixteenth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Act seeks to enable Parliament to make laws provident penalty for any person questioning the sovereignty and integrity of India. Under the provisions of the this Amendment, a person shall not be qualified to be chosen to fill a seat in Parliament or in the Legislature of State unless, inter-alia, he makers or subscribes before a person authorised by the Election Commission an oath or affirmation that he will bear true faith and allegiance to the
    Constitution and will uphold the sovereignty and integrity of India.
    </string>
<string name="seventeenthamendment">
<b>Seventeenth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Act amended the definition of the term <i>estate</i> in Article 31A to include lands held under <i>Ryotwari settlement</i> and also other lands in respect of which provisions are normally made in land reform enactments. It also amended the Ninth Schedule of the Constitution to include therein 44 State enactments related to land reforms in order to remove any uncertainty or dobut that may arise with regard to their validity.
    </string>
<string name="eighteenthamendment">
<b>Eighteenth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The amendment provides for the creation of new States, namely, Punjab and Haryana as a result of the reorganisation of the former State of Punjab and the Union Territory of Himachal Pradesh.
</string>
<string name="nineteenthamendment">
<b>Nineteenth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Act modified Article 324 so as to terminate the jurisdiction of Election Tribunals to decide election disputes. The Amendment withdrew from the Election Commission the power of setting up Election Tribunals.
    </string>
<string name="twentiethamendment">
<b>Twentieth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Act inserted a new Article 233A immediately after Article 233 in order to validate the appointment of District Judges, which might not have conformed fully to the different Constitutional requirements, which were in existent prior to 1966.
    </string>
<string name="twentyfirstamendment">
<b>Twenty-First Amendment</b> \n\n
    It amended the Eighth Schedule to the Constitution by including ‘Sindhi’ therein.
    </string>
<string name="twentysecondamendment">
<b>Twenty-Second Amendment</b> \n\n
    The amendment conferred legislative power on Parliament for the purpose of creating an autonomous Hill State within the State of Assam. Accordingly, Parliament passed the Assam Reorganization (Meghalaya) Act, 1969 to set up the State of Meghalaya within the State of Assam.
    </string>
<string name="twentythirdamendment">
<b>Twenty-Third Amendment</b> \n\n
    It deals with the questions of reservation of seat in Parliament and State Assemblies for Scheduled Castes, Scheduled Tribes and AngloIndian and further extend the period of reservation by another ten years, which means in effect thirty years from the commencement of the Constitution.
    </string>
<string name="twentyfourthamendment">
<b>Twenty-Fourth Amendment</b> \n\n
    It amended Article 13 and 368 with a view to removing all possible doubts regarding the power of Parliament to amend the Constitution and procedure thereof. It gets over the Golak Nath ruling and asserts the power of Parliament, denied to in the Golak Nath, to amend Fundamental Rights.
    </string>
<string name="twentyfifthamendment">
<b>Twenty-Fifth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The 25th amendment of the Constitution in 1971 added a new clause, Article 31C to the Constitution. Upto 1971, the position was that Fundamental Rights prevailed over the Directive Principles of State Policy and that a law enacted to implement a Directive Principle could not be valid if it conflicted with a Fundamental Right. Article 31C sought to change this relationship to some extent by conferring primacy on Articles 39(b) and 39(c) over Articles 14, 19 and 31.
    </string>
<string name="twentysixthamendment">
<b>Twenty-Sixth Amendment</b> \n\n
    It abolished Articles 291 and 362 of the Constitution and also inserted a new Article 362A after Article 363. the cumulative effect of these changes was the end of the recognition granted to the former rulers of Indian States and the abolition of Privy Purses.
    </string>
<string name="twentyseventhamendment">
<b>Twenty-Seventh Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Act was enacted to implement the decision to establish the Union Territory of Mizoram. It empowered Parliament to create a legislature and Council of Minister for the new territory.
    </string>

<string name="twentyeighthamendment">
<b>Twenty-Eighth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The amendment deleted Article 314 of the Constitution, which had given protection to the I.C.S. Officers, condition of service and privileges and inserted a new Article 312A.
    </string>
<string name="twentyninethamendment">
<b>Twenty-Nineth Amendment</b> \n\n
    By the twenty-ninth Amendment Act, 1972 two Kerala Acts dealing with land reforms were included in the 9th Schedule to the Constitution.
    </string>
<string name="thirteethamendment">
<b>Thirteeth Amendment</b> \n\n
    By this amendment, Article 133 was recast so as to redefine the Civil Appellate Jurisdiction of the Supreme Court. The result of this Amendment is that while any case involving an important question of law can reach the Supreme Court by way of appeal, a case however large the amount involved therein but involving no substantial point of law, would fail to reach the Supreme Court.
    </string>
<string name="thirtyfirstamendment">
<b>Thirty-First Amendment</b> \n\n
    By this amendment, the strength of the Lok Sabha was increased from 525 to 545 members. This was done to accommodate the increase in population as revealed by the 1971 Census. Accordingly, Article 81(i)(a) was suitably amended.
    </string>
<string name="thirtysecondamendment">
<b>Thirty-Second Amendment</b> \n\n
    The amendment Act was enacted to make few special provisions for the State of Andhra Pradash to satisfy the aspirations of the people of the Telangana region.
    </string>

<string name="thirtythirdamendment">
<b>Thirty-Third Amendment</b> \n\n
    It amended Articles 101 and 190. Before this Amendment, the resignation of a member of legislature became effective the moment it was tendered. This position is now changed. A resignation becomes effective only after it has been accepted by the Presiding Officer of the House concerned who may refuse to accept the same if he is satisfied that the resignation is not voluntary or genuine. This precautionary provision appeared to be necessary to avoid the members of Parliament or state legislatures being forced to resign.
    </string>
<string name="thirtyfourthamendment">
<b>Thirty-Fourth Amendment</b> \n\n
    By this amendment twenty State Acts concerning land ceiling and land tenure reforms were added to the Ninth Schedule to the Constitution.
    </string>

<string name="thirtyfifthamendment">
<b>Thirty-Fifth Amendment</b>\n\n
    The Constitution (Thirty-fifth and Amendment) Act, 1974-1975
    The 35th Amendment Act introduced an innovation in the Indian Constitution by conferring on Sikkim the status of an associate in the Indian Union. This was however, a shortlined experiment. The people of Sikkim desired to be and integral part of India.
    </string>
<string name="thirtysixthamendment">
<b> Thirty-Sixth Amendment </b>\n\n
    (Thirty-sixth Amendment) Act was enacted in 1975 to confer full-fledged statehood on Sikkim.
    </string>
<string name="thirtyseventhamendment">
<b> Thirty-Seventh Amendment </b>\n\n
    The Constitution (Thirty-seventh Amendment) Act, 1975
    The Amendment upgraded the status of Arunachal Pradesh as a Union Territory. Articles 239A and 240 were amended so as to authorize Parliament to create for Arunachal Pradesh a Legislature and Council of Ministers.
    </string>
<string name="thirtyeighthamendment">
<b>Thirty-Eighth Amendment</b> \n\n
    This Amendment Act was enacted during the emergency to make certain modification in the emergency provisions. The Presidential ‘satisfaction’ to issue a proclamation was declared to be final and conclusive. A classificatory clause was added to Article 356(1) so as to make Presidential ‘satisfaction’ to issue a proclamation there under as ‘final and conclusive’ which shall not be questioned in any court on any ground.
    This Amendment also declared that the ‘satisfaction’ of the President and a State Governor to issue ordinances would be ‘final and conclusive’ and shall not be questioned in any court on any ground’.
    </string>
<string name="thirtyninthamendment">
<b>Thirty-Ninth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The voiding of the election to the Lok Sabha of PM Indira Gandhi by the Allahabad High
    Court in 1975 on the petition of Raj Narain led to the enactment of the 39th Amendment Act, 1975. It introduced changes in the method deciding election disputes relating to the four high officials of the state, viz. President, VicePresident, Prime Minister and the Speaker. Under the new Article 71(2), Parliament by the law was to establish some ‘authority’ or ‘body’ for deciding such disputes, and its decisions shall not be in question any court.
    </string>
<string name="fortiethamendment">
<b>Fortieth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Amendment Act extended immunity to 64 Central and State statues by including them in the IX Schedule. These statues pertained to lad reform, Urban Ceiling and prevention of publication of objectionable matter.
    </string>
<string name="fourtyfirstamendment">
<b>Fourty-First Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Constitution (Forty-first Amendment Act), 1976 raised the age of retirement of the chairman and members of State Public Service Commissions from 60 to 62.
    </string>
<string name="fourtysecondamendment">
<b>Fourty-Second Amendment</b> \n\n
    The 42nd Constitutional Amendment Act brought a number of changes in the Constitution. The Act inter-alia gave preponderance to the Directive Principles of State Policy over the Fundamental Rights. Established the supremacy of Parliament and curtailed the powers of Judiciary. The Act was first of its kind. Is was the most comprehensive Act and touched almost all the sensitive areas of the Constitution. The Amendment was meant to enhance enormously the strength of the Government.
    The major Amendments made in the Constitution by the 42nd Amendment Act are:
    Preamble
    The characterization of India as ‘Sovereign Democratic Republic’ has been changed to ‘Sovereign Socialist Secular Democratic Republic’. The words ‘Unity of the nation’ have been changed to ‘Unity and integrity of the nation’.
    Parliament and State Legislatures : The life of the Lok Sabha and State Legislative Assemblies was extended from 5 to 6 years.
    Executive : It amended Article 74 to State explicitly that the President shall act in accordance with the advice of the Council of Ministers in discharge of his functions.
    Judiciary: The 42nd Amendment Act inserted Article 32A in order to deny the Supreme Court the power to consider the Constitutional validity of a State law. Another new provision, Article 131A, gave the Supreme Court an exclusive jurisdiction to determine question relating to the Constitutional validity of a central laws.
    Article 144A and Article 128A, the creatures of Constitutional Amendment Act made further innovation in the area of judicial review of the Constitutionality of legislation. Under Article 144A, the minimum number of judges of the Supreme Court to decide a question of a Constitutional validity of a Central or State law was fixed as at least seven and further, this required two-thirds majority of the judges sitting declare law as unconstitutional. While the power of the High Court to enforce Fundamental Rights remained untouched, several restrictions were imposed on its power to issue writs ‘for any other purpose’.
    Federalism: The Act added Article 257A in the Constitution to enable the Centre to deploy any armed force of the Union, or any other force under its control. For dealing with any grave situation of law and order in any State.
    Fundamental Rights and Directive Principles: A major change that was made by 42nd Constitutional Amendment was to give primacy to all Directive Principles over the Fundamental Rights contained in Articles 14, 19 or 31. the 42nd Constitutional Amendment added a few more Directive Principles - free legal aid, participation of workers in management of industries, protection for environment and protection of forests and wildlife of the country.
    Fundamental Duties : The 42nd Amendment Act inserted Article 51-A to create a new part called IV-A in the Constitution, which prescribed the Fundamental Duties to the citizens.
    Emergency : Prior to 42nd Amendment Act, the President could declare emergency under Article 352 throughout the country and not in a part of the country alone. The Act authorised
    the President to proclaim Emergency in any part of the country.
    The dominant thrust of the Amendment was to reduce the role of courts, particularly, that of the High Courts. It also sought to strengthen Parliament in various ways which in effect, added to the power of the Central Government, It drew enormous criticism particularly for it was pushed through during Emergency.
    </string>
<string name="fourtythirdamendment">
<b>Fourty-Third Amendment</b> \n\n
    In 1977, the Emergency came to an end and the Janata Party came into power. It made an election pledge that it would repeal the 42nd Amendment and restore the status quo ante. The 43rd Amendment repealed some of the provisions of the 42nd Amendment. Article 31D has also been omitted.
    </string>
<string name="fortyfourthamendment">
<b>Forty-Forth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The 44th Amendment passed in 1978 undid most of the distortions introduced into the Constitution by the 42nd Amendment of the Constitution. The salient features of the Amendment Act are as follows :
    • It reduced the life of Lok Sabha and State Legislative Assemblies again to five years and thus restored the status quo ante.
    • It cancelled 39th Amendment which had deprived the Supreme Court of its jurisdiction to decide disputes concerning election of the President and the Vice-President.
    • A new provision was added to Article 74(1) saying that the President could require the council of ministers to reconsider its advice to him, either generally or otherwise and the President should Act in accordance with the advice tendered after such re-consideration.
    Article 257A was Omitted
    • It has been provided that an Emergency can be proclaimed only on the basis of written advice tendered to the President by the Cabinet.
    • Right to Property has been taken out from the list of Fundamental Rights and has been declared a legal right.
    </string>
<string name="fortyfifthamendment">
<b>Forty-Fifth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The purpose of the Amendment was to continue reservation of seats for Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes in the Lok Sabha and the State Assemblies for another 10 years, i.e., upto 1990. The same concession is extended to the Anglo-Indians who may have representation by nomination in these chambers.
    </string>
<string name="fortysixthamendment">
<b>Forty-Sixth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Forty-sixth Amendment enables the State Governments to plug loopholes and realise salestax dues on the one hand and on the other aims at bringing about some uniformity in tax rates in case of certain items.
    </string>
<string name="fortyseventhamendment">
<b>Fourty-Seventh Amendment</b> \n\n
    This Amendment adds 14 State Acts dealing with land to the IXth Schedule.
    </string>
<string name="fortyeighthamendment">
<b>Fourty-Eighth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The purpose of the Amendment was to extend President’s rule in Punjab for two years. Under Article 356(5) President’s rule can last in a State for a maximum period of one year. But the conditions in Punjab did not permit holding of fresh elections and accordingly, extension of President’s rule became imperative.
    </string>
<string name="fourtyninthamendment">
<b>Fourty-Ninth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The purpose of this Amendment is to take out the Tribal areas of Tripura from Schedule V and put them in Schedule VI.
    </string>
<string name="fiftiethamendment">
<b>Fiftieth Amendment</b> \n\n
    This Amendment substitutes an expounded Article 33 for the old Article by the new Article 33, where Parliament is authorised to curtail the Fundamental Rights of the members of the armed forces, forces charged with the maintenance of public order, intelligence organisations or telecommunication systems set up for any force or Intelligence Bureau, with a view to ensure the proper discharge of duties by and maintenance of discipline among those persons in the interest of country’s security.
    </string>
<string name="fiftyfirstamendment">
<b>Fifty-First Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Amendment effectuates some changes in Articles 330 and 332 with a view to provide for reservation of seats in the Lok Sabha for Scheduled Tribes in Meghalaya, Aruncahal Pradesh and Mizoram, as well as in the Legislative Assemblies of Nagaland and Meghalaya.
    </string>
<string name="fiftysecondamendment">
<b>Fifty-Second Amendment</b> \n\n
    The amendment is designed to prevent the scourge of defection of Members of Parliament and State Legislatures from one political party to another.
    </string>

<string name="fiftythirdamendment">
<b>Fifty-Third Amendment</b> \n\n
    The amendment Act elevated the Union Territory of Mizoram to the status of a State.
    </string>
<string name="fiftyfourthamendment">
<b>Fifty-Fourth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Salaries of the Judges of the Supreme Court and the High Courts have been enhanced by the 54th Amendment Act, 1986. Accordingly, a Judge of the Supreme Court gets a salary of Rs. 9,000 per mensem and the salary of the Chief Justice is Rs. 10,000 per mensem. A Judge of the High Court gets a salary of Rs. 8,000 per mensem and the salary of the Chief Justice of the High Courts is Rs. 9,000 per mensem.
    </string>
<string name="fiftyfifthamendment">
<b>Fifty-Fifth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Union Territory of Arunchal Pradesh was elevated to the status of a State by the 55th Amendment Act.
    </string>
<string name="fiftysixthamendment">
<b>Fifty-Sixth Amendment</b> \n\n
    Constitution (56th Amendment) Act, 1987 inserted Article 394A, to make the Hindi text of the Constitution authoritative.
    </string>
<string name="fiftyseventhamendment">
<b>Fifty-Seventh Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Constitution (57th Amendment) Act, 1987 with the Goa, Daman and Diu Reorganisation Act, 1987 lifted Goa from the status of Union Territory to that of the 25th State of the Union of India.
    </string>
<string name="fiftyeighthamendment">
<b>Fifty-Eighth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Amendment Act provides the reservation of seats for tribals in the Legislative Assemblies of Arunchal Pradesh, Meghalaya, Mizoram and Nagaland.
    </string>
<string name="fiftyninthamendment">
<b>Fifty-Ninth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Act empowered the Government to impose Emergency in Punjab on the grounds that India’s integrity was threatened by internal disturbances.
    </string>
<string name="sixtiethamendment">
<b>Sixtieth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Amendment Act authorise State Governments to increase the ceiling on professional tax from Rs. 250 to Rs. 2,500 per person per annum.
    </string>
<string name="sixtyfirstamendment">
<b>Sixty-First Amendment</b> \n\n
    The 61st Amendment reduces the voting age from 21 years to 18 years for the Lok Sabha and Assembly election.
    </string>
<string name="sixtysecondamendment">
<b>Sixty-Second Amendment</b> \n\n
    The 62nd Amendment Act extends by 10 years the reservation of seats for the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes in the Lok Sabha and State Assemblies as well as nomination representatives of the Anglo-Indian community.
    </string>
<string name="sixtythirdamendment">
<b>Sixty-Third Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Amendment Act repealed the 59th Constitutional Amendment which empowered the Government to impose Emergency in Punjab.
    </string>

<string name="sixtyfourthamendment">
<b>Sixty-Fourth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Amendment Act was to extend President’s rule in Punjab for further six months.
    </string>
<string name="sixtyfifthamendment">
<b>Sixty-Fifth Amendment</b> \n\n
    Article 338 of the Constitution has been amended for the Constitution of a National Commission for Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes consisting of a chairperson,
    vice-chairperson and five other members who shall be appointed by the President by warrant under his hand and seal.
    </string>
<string name="sixtysixthamendment">
<b>Sixty-Sixth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Act protects fifty-five State Acts relating to land reforms and ceiling on agricultural land holdings, enacted by States of Andhra Pradesh, Karnataka, Kerala, Madhya Pradesh, West Bengal and Union Territory of Pondicherry, from challenge in courts, by including them in the Ninth Schedule to the Constitution.
    </string>
<string name="sixtyseventhamendment">
<b>Sixty-Seventh Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Amendment Act was to extend President’s rule in Punjab for further six months i.e., upto May 10,1991.
    </string>
<string name="sixtyeighthamendment">
<b>Sixty-Eighth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Amendment Act was to extend President’s Rule in Punjab for further six months after May 1991.
    </string>
<string name="sixtyninthamendment">
<b>Sixty-Ninth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Amendment Act was to grant  Statehood to Delhi as ‘National Capital Territory of Delhi’. It also provides a 70 member assembly and a 7 member Council of Ministers for Delhi.
    </string>
<string name="seventiethamendment">
<b>Seventieth Amendment</b> \n\n
    It facilitates for members of Delhi and Pondicherry Assemblies to participate in the election of the President.
    </string>
<string name="seventyfirstamendment">
<b>Seventy-First Amendment</b> \n\n
    The amendment facilitates for the inclusion of Nepali, Manipuri and Konkani in the Eighth Schedule of the Constitution. With the inclusion of these three languages, the number of languages in the Eight Schedule goes up to 18.
    </string>


<string name="seventysecondamendment">
<b>Seventy-Second Amendment</b> \n\n
    For restoring peace and harmony in the areas of the State of Tripura where disturbed conditions prevailed, Memorandum of Settlement was signed by the Government of India with Tripura National Volunteers on August 12,1988.
    In order to implement the said Memorandum, Article 332 of the Constitution (Seventy-second Amendment) Act, 1992 for making a temporary provision for the determination of the number of seats reserved for the Scheduled Tribes in the State Assembly of Tripura, until the re adjustment of seats is made on the basis of the first census after the year 2000 under Article 170 of the Constitution.
    </string>
<string name="seventythirdamendment">
<b>Seventy-Third Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Seventy-third Constitutional Amendment Act, 1992 was passed by the Parliament on December 22nd, 1992 which was notified by the Central Government through Official Gazette on April 20,1993 as it got rectification by the State legislatures and was assented to by the President of India. After notification, the Panchayati Raj Institutions have now got Constitutional legitimacy.
    After part VIII of the Constitution, a separate part IX has been added to the Constitution with the addition in Article 243A and fresh Schedule called Eleventh Schedule enumerating the powers and functions of Panchayti Raj Institutions. The Act provides for Gram Sabha, a three-tier model of Panchayati Raj, reservation of seats for SCs and STs in proportion to their population and one-third reservation of seats for women.
    </string>
<string name="seventyfourthamendment">
<b>Seventy-fourth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Act provides constitutional status to Urban Local Bodies. After part VIII of the Constitution, a separate part IXA has been added to the Constitution with the addition in Article 243A and a fresh schedule called Twelfth schedule enumerating the powers and functions of urban local bodies has been incorporated. The Act provides Municipal Panchayat, Municipal Council and Municipal Corporation, reservation of seats for SCs and STs in proportion to their population and one-third reservation of seats for women.
    </string>
<string name="seventyfifthamendment">
<b>Seventyfifth Amendment</b> \n\n
    It has amended Article 323-B and added a new clause (h) providing for establishment of
    tribunals for rent control cases.
    </string>
<string name="seventysixthamendment">
<b>Seventy-sixth Amendment</b> \n\n
    This Amendment Act raises the reservation quota of government jobs and seats for admission in the educational institutions in favour of socially and educationally backward classes to 69 per cent in Tamil Nadu. Further, the Amendment Act has been included in the Ninth Schedule of the Constitution to exempt it from the purview of judicial scrutiny.
    </string>
<string name="seventyseventhamendment">
<b>Seventy-Second Amendment</b> \n\n
    This Amendment has added a new clause (4-a) to Article 16 of the Constitution which empowers the State to make any provisions for reservation in promotions in Government jobs in favour of SCs and STs, if it is of opinion that they are inadequately represented in the services under the State. This has been done to nullify the effect of the Supreme Court Judgment in the Mandal Commission Case (Indra Sawhney vs. Union of India) in which the Court has held that reservation in promotions cannot be made.
    </string>
<string name="seventyeighthamendment">
<b>Seventy-Eighth Amendment</b> \n\n
    This amended the Ninth schedule of the Constitution and inserted 27 Land Reform Act of Various States in the Ninth Schedule. After this the total number of Act included in the Ninth Schedule has gone upto 284. Now these Acts cannot be challenged in the courts on the plea for the violation of Fundamental Rights.
    </string>
<string name="seventyninthamendment">
<b>Seventy-Ninth Amendment</b> \n\n
    By this Act, the Government has extended the reservation of seats for the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes as well as for the Anglo-Indians in the House of the People and in the Legislative Assemblies of the States for another ten years.
    </string>
<string name="eightiethamendment">
<b>Eightieth Amendment</b> \n\n
    Based on the recommendations of the Tenth Finance Commission, an alternative scheme for sharing taxes between the Union and the State has been enacted by the Constitution (Eightieth Amendment) Act, 2000. Under the new scheme of devolution of revenue between Union and the states, 26 per cent out of gross proceeds of Union taxes and duties is to be assigned to the States in lieu of their existing share in the income-tax, excise duties special excise duties and grants in lieu of tax on railway passenger fares.
    </string>
<string name="eightyfirstamendment">
<b>Eighty-First Amendment</b> \n\n
    By this amendment the unfilled vacancies of a year which reserved for the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes for being filled up in that year in accordance with any provision of reservations made under Article 16 of the Constitution shall be considered as a separate class of vacancies to be filled up in any succeeding year or years, and such class of vacancies shall not be considered together with the vacancies of the year in which they were filled up for determining the ceiling of fifty per cent reservation against total number of vacancies of that year.
    </string>

<string name="eightysecondamendment">
<b>Eighty-Second Amendment</b> \n\n
    The amendment provides that nothing in Article 335 shall prevent the State from making any provisions in favour of the members of the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes for relaxation in qualifying marks in any examination or lowering the standards of evaluation for reservation in matters of promotion to any class or classes of services or posts in connection with affairs of the Union or of a State.
    </string>
<string name="eightythirdamendment">
<b>Eighty-Third Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Act amended Article 243M of the Constitution to provide that no reservation in Panchayats need be made in favour of the Scheduled Castes in Arunachal Pradesh wholly inhabited by tribal population.
    </string>
<string name="eightyfourthamendment">
<b>Eighty-Fourth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Act amended provisions to Article 82 and 170(3) of the Constitution to readjust and rationalise the territorial constituencies in the States, without altering the number of seats allotted to each State in the House of People and Legislative Assemblies of the States, including the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes Constituencies, on the basis of the population ascertained at the census for the year 1991 so as
    to remove the imbalance caused due to uneven growth of population/electorate in different constituencies.
    </string>
<string name="eightyfifthamendment">
<b>Eighty-Fifth Amendment</b> \n\n
    This Act amended Article 16 (4A) of the Constitution to provide for consequential seniority in the case of promotion by virtue of rule of reservation for Government servants belonging to the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes.
    </string>
<string name="eightysixthamendment">
<b>Eighty-Sixth Amendment</b> \n\n
    With a view to making right to free and compulsory education a fundamental right, the Act inserts a new Article, namely, Article 21A conferring on all children in the age group of 6 to 14 years the right to free and compulsory education. The Act amends in Part-III, Part –IV and Part-IV(A) of the Constitution.
    </string>
<string name="eightyseventhamendment">
<b>Eighty-Seventh Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Amendment provides for readjustment of electoral constituencies, including those reserved for the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes, based on the population census for the year 2001, without affecting the number of seats allocated to States in the legislative bodies.
    </string>


<string name="eightyeighthamendment">
<b>Eighty-Eighth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Act amends Article 268, 270 and VIIth Schedule of the Constitution. It adds 92C just after 92B and makes provisions for Tax on Services.
    </string>
<string name="eightyninthamendment">
<b>Eighty-Ninth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Act adds Article 338A and provides for the creation of National Commission for Scheduled Tribes.
    </string>
<string name="ninetiethamendment">
<b>Ninetieth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Act amends Article 332 and adds section (6) regarding representation in the Bodo Territorial Areas District in the State of Assam.
    </string>

<string name="ninetyonethamendment">
<b>Ninety-Oneth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Act makes provisions for limiting the size of the Council of Ministers at the Center and in the States and gives teeth to debar a defector from holding any remunerative political post for the remaining tenure of the legislature unless reelected.
    </string>
<string name="ninetysecondamendment">
<b>Ninety-Second Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Amendment facilitates for the inclusion of Bodo, Dogari, Maithili and Santhali in the VIIIth Schedule of the Constitution. With the inclusion of these four languages, the number of languages in the VIIIth Schedule goes upto 22.
    </string>
<string name="ninetythirdamendment">
<b>Ninety-Third Amendment</b> \n\n
    Providing reservation for the socially and educationally backward classes, besides the Schedules Castes and the Scheduled Tribes, in private unaided educational institutions.
    </string>
<string name="ninetyfourthamendment">
<b>Ninety-Fourth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The Constitution provides that there shall be Minister in charge of tribal welfare who may in addition be in charge of the welfare of the Scheduled Casts and backward classes or any other work in the State of Bihar, Madhya Pradesh and Orissa.
    </string>
<string name="ninetyfifthamendment">
<b>Ninety-Fifth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The amendment aims to extend the reservation of seats for SCs and STs in the Lok Sabha and States, assemblies from Sixty years to Seventy years.
    </string>
<string name="ninetysixthamendment">
<b>Ninety-Sixth Amendment</b> \n\n
    It has substituted "Odiat" for "Oriyat".
    </string>
<string name="ninetyseventhamendment">
<b>Ninety-Seventh Amendment</b> \n\n
    Added the words "or co-operative societiest" after the word "or unionst" in Article 19(l)(c) and insertion of Article 43B i.e., Promotion of Cooperative Societies and added Part-IXB i.e., The Co-operative Societies.
    The objective of amendment is to encourage economic activities of cooperatives which in turn help progress of rural India. It is expected to not only ensure autonomous and democratic functioning of cooperatives, but also the accountability of the management to the members and other stakeholders.
    </string>
<string name="ninetyeighthamendment">
<b>Ninety-Eighth Amendment</b> \n\n
    To empower the Governor of Karnataka to take steps to develop the Hyderabad-Karnataka Region.
    </string>
<string name="ninetyninthamendment">
<b>Ninety-Ninth Amendment</b> \n\n
    The amendment provides for the formation of a National Judicial Appointments Commission. 16 State assemblies out of 29 States including Goa, Rajasthan, Tripura, Gujarat and Telangana ratified the Central Legislation, enabling thePresident of India to give assent to the bill. The amendment is in toto quashed by Supreme Court on 16 October 2015.
    </string>
<string name="hundredthamendment">
<b>Hundredth Amendment</b> \n\n
    Exchange of certain enclave territories with Bangladesh and conferment of citizenship rights to residents of enclaves consequent to signing of Land Boundary Agreement (LBA) Treaty between India and Bangladesh.
</string>


    <string name="firstschedule">
    <b>First schedule</b>
    [Articles 1 and 4]\n\n
    I. THE STATES\n\n
    1.Andhra Pradesh:-\n\n

    The territories specified in sub-section (1) of section 3 of the Andhra
    State Act, 1953, sub-section (1) of section 3 of the States Reorganisation Act,
    1956, the First Schedule to the Andhra Pradesh and Madras (Alteration of
    Boundaries) Act, 1959, and the Schedule to the Andhra Pradesh and Mysore
    (Transfer of Territory) Act, 1968, but excluding the territories specified in the
    Second Schedule to the Andhra Pradesh and Madras (Alteration of
    Boundaries) Act, 1959.\n\n
    2. Assam:-\n\n
    The territories which immediately before the commencement of this
    Constitution were comprised in the Province of Assam, the Khasi States and
    the Assam Tribal Areas, but excluding the territories specified in the Schedule
    to the Assam (Alteration of Boundaries) Act, 1951 and the territories
    specified in sub-section (1) of section 3 of the State of Nagaland Act, 1962
    and the territories specified in sections 5, 6 and 7 of the North-Eastern Areas
    (Reorganisation) Act, 1971.\n\n
    3. Bihar:-\n\n
    The territories which immediately before the commencement of this
    Constitution were either comprised in the Province of Bihar or were being
    administered as if they formed part of that Province and the territories
    specified in clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 3 of the Bihar and Uttar
    Pradesh (Alteration of Boundaries) Act, 1968, but excluding the territories
    specified in sub-section (1) of section 3 of the Bihar and West Bengal
    (Transfer of Territories) Act, 1956, and the territories specified in clause (b)
    of sub-section (1) of section 3 of the first mentioned Act and the territories
    specified in section 3 of the Bihar Reorganisation Act, 2000.\n\n
    4. Gujarat:-\n\n
    The territories referred to in sub-section (1) of section 3 of the Bombay
    Reorganisation Act, 1960.\n\n
    5. Kerala:-\n\n
    The territories specified in sub-section (1) of section 5 of the States
    Reorganisation Act, 1956.\n\n
    6. Madhya Pradesh:-\n\n
    The territories specified in sub-section (1) of section 9 of the States
    Reorganisation Act, 1956 and the First Schedule to the Rajasthan and Madhya
    Pradesh (Transfer of Territories) Act, 1959 but excluding the territories
    specified in section 3 of the Madhya Pradesh Reorganisation Act, 2000.\n\n

    7. Tamil Nadu:-\n\n
    The territories which immediately before the commencement of this
    Constitution were either comprised in the Province of Madras or were being
    administered as if they formed part of that Province and the territories
    specified in section 4 of the States Reorganisation Act, 1956, and the Second
    Schedule to the Andhra Pradesh and Madras (Alteration of Boundaries) Act,
    1959, but excluding the territories specified in sub-section (1) of section 3 and
    sub-section (1) of section 4 of the Andhra State Act, 1953 and the territories
    specified in clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 5, section 6 and clause (d)
    of sub-section (1) of section 7 of the States Reorganisation Act, 1956 and the
    territories specified in the First Schedule to the Andhra Pradesh and Madras
    (Alteration of Boundaries) Act, 1959.\n\n
    8. Maharashtra:-\n\n
    The territories specified in sub-section (1) of section 8 of the States
    Reorganisation Act, 1956, but excluding the territories referred to in subsection
    (1)	of section 3 of the Bombay Reorganisation Act, 1960.\n\n
    9. Karnataka:-\n\n
    The territories specified in sub-section (1) of section 7 of the States
    Reorganisation Act, 1956 but excluding the territory specified in the Schedule
    to the Andhra Pradesh and Mysore (Transfer of Territory) Act, 1968.\n\n

    10. Orissa:-\n\n
    The territories which immediately before the commencement of this
    Constitution were either comprised in the Province of Orissa or were being
    administered as if they formed part of that Province.\n\n
    11. Punjab:-\n\n
    The territories specified in section 11 of the States Reorganisation Act,
    1956 and the territories referred to in Part II of the First Schedule to the
    Acquired Territories (Merger) Act, 1960 but excluding the territories referred
    to in Part II of the First Schedule to the Constitution (Ninth Amendment) Act,
    1960 and the territories specified in sub-section (1) of section 3, section 4 and
    sub-section (1) section 5 of the Punjab Reorganisation Act, 1966.\n\n

    12. Rajasthan:-\n\n
    The territories specified in section 10 of the States Reorganisation Act, 1956
    but excluding the territories specified in the First Schedule to the Rajasthan
    and Madhya Pradesh (Transfer of Territories) Act, 1959.\n\n

    13. Uttar Pradesh:-\n\n
    The territories which immediately before the commencement of this
    Constitution were either comprised in the Province known as the United
    Provinces or were being administered as if they formed part of that Province,
    the territories specified in clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 3 of the
    Bihar and Uttar Pradesh (Alteration of Boundaries) Act, 1968, and the
    territories specified in clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 4 of the Haryana
    and Uttar Pradesh (Alteration of Boundaries) Act, 1979, but excluding the
    territories specified in clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 3 of the Bihar
    and Uttar Pradesh (Alteration of Boundaries) Act, 1968, and the territories
    specified in section 3 of the Uttar Pradesh Reorganisation Act, 2000 and the
    territories specified in clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 4 of the Haryana
    and Uttar Pradesh (Alteration of Boundaries) Act, 1979.\n\n
    14. West Bengal:-\n\n
    The territories which immediately before the commencement of this
    Constitution were either comprised in the Province of West Bengal or were
    being administered as if they formed part of that Province and the territory of
    Chandernagore as defined in clause (c) of section 2 of the Chandernagore
    (Merger) Act, 1954 and also the territories specified in sub-section (1) of
    section 3 of the Bihar and West Bengal (Transfer of Territories) Act, 1956.\n\n
    15. Jammu and Kashmir:-\n\n
    The territory which immediately before the commencement of this
    Constitution was comprised in the Indian State of Jammu and Kashmir./n/n
    16. Nagaland:-\n\n
    The territories specified in sub-section (1) of section 3 of the State of
    Nagaland Act, 1962.\n\n
    17. Haryana:-\n\n
    The territories specified in sub-section (1) of section 3 of the Punjab
    Reorganisation Act, 1966 and the territories specified in clause (a) of subsection
    (1) of section 4 of the Haryana and Uttar Pradesh (Alteration of
    Boundaries) Act, 1979, but excluding the territories specified in clause (v) of
    sub-section (1) of section 4 of that Act.\n\n
    18. Himachal Pradesh:-\n\n
    The territories which immediately before the commencement
    of this Constitution were being administered as if they were Chief
    Commissioners’ Provinces under the names of Himachal Pradesh and
    Bilaspur and the territories specified in sub-section (1) of section 5 of the
    Punjab Reorganisation Act, 1966.\n\n
    19. Manipur:-\n\n
    The territory which immediately before the commencement of this
    Constitution was being administered as if it were a Chief Commissioner’s
    Province under the name of Manipur.\n\n
    20.Tripura:-\n\n
    The territory which immediately before the commencement of this
    Constitution was being administered as if it were a Chief Commissioner’s
    Province under the name of Tripura.\n\n
    21. Meghalaya:-\n\n
    The territories specified in section 5 of the North-Eastern Areas
    (Reorganisation) Act, 1971.\n\n
    22. Sikkim:-\n\n
    The territories which immediately before the commencement of the
    Constitution (Thirty-sixth Amendment) Act, 1975, were comprised in Sikkim.\n\n

    23. Mizoram:-\n\n
    The territories specified in section 6 of the North-Eastern Areas
    (Reorganisation) Act, 1971.\n\n
    24. Arunachal Pradesh:-\n\n
    The territories specified in section 7 of the North-Eastern Areas
    (Reorganisation) Act, 1971.\n\n

    25. Goa:-\n\n
    The territories specified in section 3 of the Goa, Daman and Diu
    Reorganisation Act, 1987.\n\n
    26. Chhattisgarh:-\n\n
    The territories specified in section 3 of the Madhya Pradesh Reorganisation
    Act, 2000.\n\n
    27. Uttaranchal :-\n\n
    The territories specified in section 3 of the Uttar Pradesh
    Reorganisation Act, 2000.\n\n
    28. Jharkhand:-\n\n
    The territories specified in section 3 of the Bihar
    Reorganisation Act, 2000.\n\n
    <b>II. THE UNION TERRITORIES</b>
    1.	Delhi:-\n\n
    The territory which immediately before the commencement of
    this Constitution was comprised in the Chief Commissioner’s Province of
    Delhi.\n\n
    * * * * *
    * * * * *
    2.The Andaman and The Nicobar islands:-\n\n
    The territory which immediately before the commencement of
    Nicobar Islands this Constitution was comprised in the Chief
    Commissioner’s Province of the Andaman and Nicobar Islands.\n\n
    3.Lakshadweep:-\n\n
    The territory specified in section 6 of the States
    Reorganisation Act, 1956.\n\n
    4. Dadra and Nagar Havelli:-\n\n
    The territory which immediately before the eleventh day of
    Nagar Haveli August 1961 was comprised in Free Dadra and Nagar Haveli.\n\n
    5. Daman and Diu:-\n\n
    The territories specified in section 4 of the Goa, Daman
    and Diu Reorganisation Act, 1987.\n\n
    6. Pondicherry:-\n\n
    The territories which immediately before the sixteenth day of
    August, 1962, were comprised in the French Establishments in India known
    as Pondicherry, Karikal, Mahe and Yanam.\n\n
    7. Chandigarh:-\n\n
    The territories specified in section 4 of the Punjab
    Reorganisation Act, 1966.\n\n
    * * * * *
    * * * * *</string>



<string name="secondschedule">
<b>SECOND SCHEDULE</b>\n\n
    [Articles 59(3), 65(3), 75(6), 97, 125, 148(3), 158(3),
    164(5), 186 and 221]\n\n
<b>PART A</b>
<b>PROVISIONS AS TO THE PRESIDENT AND THE GOVERNORS OF STATES</b>\n\n

    1. There shall be paid to the President and to the Governors of the States the following
    emoluments per mensem, that is to say:—\n\n
    The President .. 10,000 rupees*.(Now 1,50,000 rupees, vide ACT 28 Of 2008, s.2(w.e.f 1-1-2006)\n\n
    The Governor of a State .. 5,500 rupees+.(Now 1,10,000 rupees, vide ACT 1 Of 2009, s.3(w.e.f 1-1-2006)\n\n
    2. There shall also be paid to the President and to the Governors of the States such allowances
    as were payable respectively to the Governor-General of the Dominion of India and to the
    Governors of the corresponding Provinces immediately before the commencement of this
    Constitution.\n\n
    3. The President and the Governors of the States throughout their respective terms of office shall
    be entitled to the same privileges to which the Governor-General and the Governors of the
    corresponding Provinces were respectively entitled immediately before the commencement of this
    Constitution.\n\n
    4. While the Vice-President or any other person is discharging the functions of, or is acting as,
    President, or any person is discharging the functions of the Governor, he shall be entitled to the
    same emoluments, allowances and privileges as the President or the Governor whose functions he
    discharges or for whom he acts, as the case may be.\n\n
    * * * * *
<b>PART C</b>
<b>PROVISIONS AS TO THE SPEAKER AND THE DEPUTY SPEAKER OF THE HOUSE OF THE
PEOPLE AND THE CHAIRMAN AND THE DEPUTY CHAIRMAN
OF THE COUNCIL OF STATES AND THE SPEAKER AND THE
DEPUTY SPEAKER OF THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY
AND THE CHAIRMAN AND THE DEPUTY
CHAIRMAN OF THE LEGISLATIVE
COUNCIL OF A STATE</b>
    7. There shall be paid to the Speaker of the House of the People and the Chairman of the
    Council of States such salaries and allowances as were payable to the Speaker of the Constituent
    Assembly of the Dominion of India immediately before the commencement of this Constitution,
    and there shall be paid to the Deputy Speaker of the House of the People and to the Deputy
    Chairman of the Council of States such salaries and allowances as were payable to the Deputy
    Speaker of the Constituent Assembly of the Dominion of India immediately before such
    commencement.\n\n
    8. There shall be paid to the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker of the Legislative Assembly and
    to the Chairman and the Deputy Chairman of the Legislative Council of a State such salaries and
    allowances as were payable respectively to the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker of the Legislative
    Assembly and the President and the Deputy President of the Legislative Council of the
    corresponding Province immediately before the commencement of this Constitution and, where
    the corresponding Province had no Legislative Council immediately before such commencement,
    there shall be paid to the Chairman and the Deputy Chairman of the Legislative Council of the
    State such salaries and allowances as the Governor of the State may determine.\n\n

<b>PART D</b>

<b>PROVISIONS AS TO THE JUDGES OF THE SUPREME COURT AND OF THE HIGH COURTS</b>

    9. (1) There shall be paid to the Judges of the Supreme Court, in respect of time spent on actual
    service, salary at the following rates per mensem, that is to say:—\n\n

    The Chief Justice .. 10,000 rupees. (Now 1,00,000 rupees, vide ACT 23 Of 2009, s.8(w.e.f 1-1-2006)\n
    Any other Judge .. 9,000 rupees. (Now 90,000 rupees, vide s.8 ibid. (w.e.f 1-1-2006)\n
    Provided that if a Judge of the Supreme Court at the time of his appointment is in receipt of a
    pension (other than a disability or wound pension) in respect of any previous service under the
    Government of India or any of its predecessor Governments or under the Government of a State or
    any of its predecessor Governments, his salary in respect of service in the Supreme Court shall be
    reduced—\n\n
    (a) by the amount of that pension, and\n\n
    (b) if he has, before such appointment, received in lieu of a portion of the
    pension due to him in respect of such previous service the commuted value thereof,
    by the amount of that portion of the pension, and\n\n
    (c) if he has, before such appointment, received a retirement gratuity in respect
    of such previous service, by the pension equivalent of that gratuity.\n\n
    (2) Every Judge of the Supreme Court shall be entitled without payment of rent to the use of an
    official residence.\n\n
    (3) Nothing in sub-paragraph (2) of this paragraph shall apply to a Judge who, immediately
    before the commencement of this Constitution,—\n\n
    (a) was holding office as the Chief Justice of the Federal Court and has become
    on such commencement the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court under clause (1) of
    article 374, or\n
    (b) was holding office as any other Judge of the Federal Court and has on such
    commencement become a Judge (other than the Chief Justice) of the Supreme Court
    under the said clause,
    during the period he holds office as such Chief Justice or other Judge, and every Judge who so
    becomes the Chief Justice or other Judge of the Supreme Court shall, in respect of time spent on
    actual service as such Chief Justice or other Judge, as the case may be, be entitled to receive in
    addition to the salary specified in sub-paragraph (1) of this paragraph as special pay an amount
    equivalent to the difference between the salary so specified and the salary which he was drawing
    immediately before such commencement.\n\n
    (4) Every Judge of the Supreme Court shall receive such reasonable allowances to reimburse
    him for expenses incurred in travelling on duty within the territory of India and shall be afforded
    such reasonable facilities in connection with travelling as the President may from time to time
    prescribe.\n\n
    (5) The rights in respect of leave of absence (including leave allowances) and pension of the
    Judges of the Supreme Court shall be governed by the provisions which, immediately before the
    commencement of this Constitution, were applicable to the Judges of the Federal Court.\n\n
    10. (1) There shall be paid to the Judges of High Courts, in respect of time spent on actual
    service, salary at the following rates per mensem, that is to say,—\n\n
    The Chief Justice .. 9,000 rupees. (Now 90,000 rupees, vide ACT 23 Of 2009, s.2(w.e.f 1-1-2006)\n\n
    Any other Judge .. 8,000 rupees. (Now 80,000 rupees, vide, s.2 ibid. (w.e.f 1-1-2006)\n\n
    Provided that if a Judge of a High Court at the time of his appointment is in receipt of a pension
    (other than a disability or wound pension) in respect of any previous service under the
    Government of India or any of its predecessor Governments or under the Government of a State
    or any of its predecessor Governments, his salary in respect of service in the High Court shall be
    reduced—\n\n
    (a) by the amount of that pension, and\n
    (b) if he has, before such appointment, received in lieu of a portion of the
    pension due to him in respect of such previous service the commuted value thereof,
    by the amount of that portion of the pension, and\n
    (c) if he has, before such appointment, received a retirement gratuity in respect
    of such previous service, by the pension equivalent of that gratuity.\n
    (2) Every person who immediately before the commencement of this Constitution—\n\n
    (a) was holding office as the Chief Justice of a High Court in any Province and
    has on such commencement become the Chief Justice of the High Court in the
    corresponding State under clause (1) of article 376, or\n
    (b) was holding office as any other Judge of a High Court in any Province and
    has on such commencement become a Judge (other than the Chief Justice) of the
    High Court in the corresponding State under the said clause,
    shall, if he was immediately before such commencement drawing a salary at a rate higher than that
    specified in sub-paragraph (1) of this paragraph, be entitled to receive in respect of time spent on
    actual service as such Chief Justice or other Judge, as the case may be, in addition to the salary
    specified in the said sub-paragraph as special pay an amount equivalent to the difference between
    the salary so specified and the salary which he was drawing immediately before such
    commencement.\n\n
    (3) Any person who, immediately before the commencement of the Constitution (Seventh
    Amendment) Act, 1956, was holding office as the Chief Justice of the High Court of a State
    specified in Part B of the First Schedule and has on such commencement become the Chief Justice
    of the High Court of a State specified in the said Schedule as amended by the said Act, shall, if he
    was immediately before such commencement drawing any amount as allowance in addition to his
    salary, be entitled to receive in respect of time spent on actual service as such Chief Justice, the
    same amount as allowance in addition to the salary specified in sub-paragraph (1) of this
    paragraph.\n\n
    11. In this Part, unless the context otherwise requires,—\n\n
    (a) the expression “Chief Justice" includes an acting Chief Justice, and a
    “Judge" includes an ad hoc Judge;\n\n
    (b) “actual service" includes—\n
    (i) time spent by a Judge on duty as a Judge or in the performance of such
    other functions as he may at the request of the President undertake to discharge;\n
    (ii) vacations, excluding any time during which the Judge is absent on leave;
    And\n
    (iii) joining time on transfer from a High Court to the Supreme Court or
    from one High Court to another.\n\n
<b>PART E</b>/n/n
<b>PROVISIONS AS TO THE COMPTROLLER AND
AUDITOR-GENERAL OF INDIA</b>\n\n
    12. (1) There shall be paid to the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India a salary at the rate of
    * four thousand rupees per mensem.\n\n
    (2) The person who was holding office immediately before the commencement of this
    Constitution as Auditor-General of India and has become on such commencement the Comptroller
    and Auditor-General of India under artcle 377 shall in addition to the salary specified in subparagraph
    (1) of this paragraph be entitled to receive as special pay an amount equivalent to the
    difference between the salary so specified and the salary which he was drawing as Auditor-
    General of India immediately before such commencement.\n\n
    (3) The rights in respect of leave of absence and pension and the other conditions of service of
    the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India shall be governed or shall continue to be governed,
    as the case may be, by the provisions which were applicable to the Auditor-General of India
    immediately before the commencement of this Constitution and all references in those provisions
    to the Governor-General shall be construed as references to the President.\n\n</string>
<string name="thirdschedule">
<b>THIRD SCHEDULE</b>\n
    [Articles 75(4), 99, 124(6), 148(2), 164(3), 188 and 219](see also arts. 84(a) and 173 (a))\n\n
<b>Forms of Oaths or Affirmations</b>\n\n
<b>I</b>\n\n
    Form of oath of office for a Minister for the Union:—\n\n
    “I, A.B., do swear in the name of God that I will bear true faith and
    solemnly affirm
    allegiance to the Constitution of India as by law established, that I will uphold the sovereignty and
    integrity of India, that I will faithfully and conscientiously discharge my duties as a Minister for
    the Union and that I will do right to all manner of people in accordance with the Constitution and
    the law, without fear or favour, affection or ill-will."\n\n
<b>II</b>\n\n
    Form of oath of secrecy for a Minister for the Union:—
    “I, A.B., do swear in the name of God that I will not directly or indirectly
    solemnly affirm
    communicate or reveal to any person or persons any matter which shall be brought under my
    consideration or shall become known to me as a Minister for the Union except as may be required
    for the due discharge of my duties as such Minister."\n\n
<b>III</b>\n\n
<b>A</b>\n\n
    Form of oath or affirmation to be made by a candidate for election to Parliament:—
    “I, A.B., having been nominated as a candidate to fill a seat in the Council of States (or the
    House of the People) do swear in the name of God that I will bear true faith
    solemnly affirm
    and allegiance to the Constitution of India as by law established and that I will uphold the
    sovereignty and integrity of India."\n\n
<b>B</b>\n\n
    Form of oath or affirmation to be made by a member of Parliament:—
    “I, A.B., having been elected (or nominated) a member of the Council of States (or the House of
    the People) do swear in the name of God that I will bear true faith and allegiance
    solemnly affirm
    to the Constitution of India as by law established, that I will uphold the sovereignty and integrity
    of India and that I will faithfully discharge the duty upon which I am about to enter."\n\n
<b>IV</b>\n\n
    Form of oath or affirmation to be made by the Judges of the Supreme Court and the Comptroller
    and Auditor-General of India:—\n\n
    “I, A.B., having been appointed Chief Justice (or a Judge) of the Supreme Court of India
    (or Comptroller and Auditor-General of India) do swear in the name of God that I
    solemnly affirm
    will bear true faith and allegiance to the Constitution of India as by law established, that I
    will uphold the sovereignty and integrity of India, that I will duly and faithfully and to the best of
    my ability, knowledge and judgment perform the duties of my office without fear or favour,
    affection or ill-will and that I will uphold the Constitution and the laws."\n\n
<b>V</b>\n\n
    Form of oath of office for a Minister for a State:—
    “I, A.B., do swear in the name of God that I will bear true faith and allegiance to the
    solemnly affirm
    Constitution of India as by law established, that I will uphold the sovereignty and integrity of
    India, that I will faithfully and conscientiously discharge my duties as a Minister for the State of
    ..........and that I will do right to all manner of people in accordance with the Constitution and the
    law without fear or favour, affection or ill-will."\n\n
<b>VI</b>\n\n
    Form of oath of secrecy for a Minister for a State:—
    “I, A.B., do swear in the name of God that I will not directly or indirectly
    solemnly affirm
    communicate or reveal to any person or persons any matter which shall be brought under my
    consideration or shall become known to me as a Minister for the State of ....................except as
    may be required for the due discharge of my duties as such Minister."\n\n
<b>VII</b>\n\n
<b>A</b>\n\n
    Form of oath or affirmation to be made by a candidate for election to the Legislature of a
    State:—\n\n
    “I, A.B., having been nominated as a candidate to fill a seat in the Legislative Assembly (or
    Legislative Council), do swear in the name of God that I will bear true
    solemnly affirm
    faith and allegiance to the Constitution of India as by law established and that I will uphold the
    sovereignty and integrity of India."\n\n
<b>B</b>\n\n
    Form of oath or affirmation to be made by a member of the Legislature of a State:—\n\n
    “I, A.B., having been elected (or nominated) a member of the Legislative Assembly (or
    Legislative Council), do swear in the name of God that I will bear true faith and
    solemnly affirm
    allegiance to the Constitution of India as by law established, that I will uphold the sovereignty and
    integrity of India and that I will faithfully discharge the duty upon which I am about to enter."\n\n
<b>VIII</b>\n\n
    Form of oath or affirmation to be made by the Judges of a High Court:—\n\n
    “I, A.B., having been appointed Chief Justice (or a Judge) of the High Court at (or of)
    ..........do swear in the name of God that I will bear true faith and allegiance to
    solemnly affirm
    the Constitution of India as by law established, that I will uphold the sovereignty and integrity of
    India, that I will duly and faithfully and to the best of my ability, knowledge and judgment
    perform the duties of my office without fear or favour, affection or ill-will and that I will uphold
    the Constitution and the laws."\n\n</string>
<string name="fourthschedule">
    <b>FOURTH SCHEDULE</b>\n\n
    [Articles 4(1) and 80(2)]\n\n
    Allocation of seats in the Council of States\n\n
    To each State or Union territory specified in the first column of the following table, there shall
    be allotted the number of seats specified in the second column thereof opposite to that State or that
    Union territory, as the case may be.\n\n
    TABLE
    1. Andhra Pradesh………………………………………………… 18\n
    2. Assam ………………………………………………………….. 7\n
    3. Bihar…………………………………………………………….. 16\n
    4. Jharkhand……………………………………………………….. 6\n
    5. Goa……………………………………………………………….. 1\n
    6. Gujarat……………………………………………………………. 11\n
    7. Haryana…………………………………………………………… 5\n
    8. Kerala…………………………………………………………….. 9\n
    9. Madhya Pradesh…………………………………………………. 11\n
    10. Chhattisgarh……………………………………………………… 5\n
    11. Tamil Nadu ……………………………………………………… 18\n
    12. Maharashtra………………………………………………………… 19\n
    13. Karnataka…………………………………………………………. 12\n
    14. Orissa……………………………………………………………… 10\n
    15. Punjab……………………………………………………………… 7\n
    16. Rajasthan………………………………………………………….. 10\n
    17. Uttar Pradesh………………………………………………………. 31\n
    18. Uttaranchal………………………………………………………… 3\n
    19. West Bengal……………………………………………………….. 16\n
    20. Jammu and Kashmir………………………………………………. 4\n
    21. Nagaland……………………………………………………………. 1\n
    22. Himachal Pradesh…………………………………………………. 3\n
    23. Manipur…………………………………………………………….. 1\n
    24. Tripura………………………………………………………………. 1\n
    25. Meghalaya…………………………………………………………. 1\n
    26. Sikkim………………………………………………………………. 1\n
    27. Mizoram…………………………………………………………….. 1\n
    28. Arunachal Pradesh……………………………………………….. 1\n
    29. Delhi………………………………………………………………… 3\n
    30. Pondicherry………………………………………………………… 1\n\n
<b>TOTAL</b>……………………………………………… 233\n
    \n</string>
<string name="fifthschedule">
<b>FIFTH SCHEDULE</b>\n\n
    [Article 244(1)]\n\n
    Provisions as to the Administration and Control of Scheduled Areas and Scheduled
    Tribes\n\n
<b>PART A</b>\n
<b>GENERAL</b>\n\n
    1. Interpretation.—In this Schedule, unless the context otherwise requires, the expression
    “State" does not include the States of Assam, Meghalaya, Tripura and Mizoram.\n\n
    2. Executive power of a State in Scheduled Areas.—Subject to the provisions of this
    Schedule, the executive power of a State extends to the Scheduled Areas therein.\n\n
    3. Report by the Governor to the President regarding the administration of Scheduled
    Areas.—The Governor of each State having Scheduled Areas therein shall annually, or whenever
    so required by the President, make a report to the President regarding the administration of the
    Scheduled Areas in that State and the executive power of the Union shall extend to the giving of
    directions to the State as to the administration of the said areas.\n\n
<b>PART B</b>\n
<b>ADMINISTRATION AND CONTROL OF SCHEDULED AREAS AND SCHEDULED TRIBES</b>\n\n
    4. Tribes Advisory Council.—(1) There shall be established in each State having Scheduled
    Areas therein and, if the President so directs, also in any State having Scheduled Tribes but not
    Scheduled Areas therein, a Tribes Advisory Council consisting of not more than twenty members
    of whom, as nearly as may be, three-fourths shall be the representatives of the Scheduled Tribes in
    the Legislative Assembly of the State:\n\n
    Provided that if the number of representatives of the Scheduled Tribes in the Legislative
    Assembly of the State is less than the number of seats in the Tribes Advisory Council to be filled
    by such representatives, the remaining seats shall be filled by other members of those tribes.\n\n
    (2) It shall be the duty of the Tribes Advisory Council to advise on such matters pertaining to the
    welfare and advancement of the Scheduled Tribes in the State as may be referred to them by the
    Governor.\n\n
    (3) The Governor may make rules prescribing or regulating, as the case may be,—\n\n
    (a) the number of members of the Council, the mode of their appointment and the
    appointment of the Chairman of the Council and of the officers and servants thereof;\n\n
    (b) the conduct of its meetings and its procedure in general; and\n\n
    (c) all other incidental matters.\n\n
    5. Law applicable to Scheduled Areas.—(1) Notwithstanding anything in this Constitution, the
    Governor may by public notification direct that any particular Act of Parliament or of the
    Legislature of the State shall not apply to a Scheduled Area or any part thereof in the
    State or shall apply to a Scheduled Area or any part thereof in the State subject to such
    exceptions and modifications as he may specify in the notification and
    any direction given under this sub-paragraph may be given so as to have retrospective effect.\n\n
    (2) The Governor may make regulations for the peace and good government of any area in a
    State which is for the time being a Scheduled Area.
    In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such regulations
    may—\n\n
    (a) prohibit or restrict the transfer of land by or among members of the Scheduled Tribes in
    such area;\n\n
    (b) regulate the allotment of land to members of the Scheduled Tribes in such area;\n\n
    (c) regulate the carrying on of business as money-lender by persons who lend money to
    members of the Scheduled Tribes in such area.\n\n
    (3) In making any such regulation as is referred to in sub-paragraph (2) of this paragraph, the
    Governor may repeal or amend any Act of Parliament or of the Legislature of the State or any
    existing law which is for the time being applicable to the area in question.\n\n
    (4) All regulations made under this paragraph shall be submitted forthwith to the President and,
    until assented to by him, shall have no effect.\n\n
    (5) No regulation shall be made under this paragraph unless the Governor making the regulation
    has, in the case where there is a Tribes Advisory Council for the State, consulted such Council.\n\n
<b>PART C</b>\n
<b>SCHEDULED AREAS</b>\n\n
    6. Scheduled Areas.—(1) In this Constitution, the expression “Scheduled Areas" means such
    areas as the President may by order,
    declare to be Scheduled Areas.\n\n
    (2) The President may at any time by order\n\n
    (a) direct that the whole or any specified part of a Scheduled Area shall cease to be a
    Scheduled Area or a part of such an area;\n\n
    (aa) increase the area of any Scheduled Area in a State after consultation with the Governor
    of that State;\n\n
    (b) alter, but only by way of rectification of boundaries, any Scheduled Area;\n\n
    (c) on any alteration of the boundaries of a State or on the admission into the Union or the
    establishment of a new State, declare any territory not previously included in any State to be, or
    to form part of, a Scheduled Area;\n\n
    (d) rescind, in relation to any State or States, any order or orders made under this paragraph,
    and in consultation with the Governor of the State concerned, make fresh orders redefining the
    areas which are to be Scheduled Areas;
    and any such order may contain such incidental and consequential provisions as appear to the
    President to be necessary and proper, but save as aforesaid, the order made under sub-paragraph\n\n
    (1) of this paragraph shall not be varied by any subsequent order.\n\n
<b>PART D</b>\n
<b>AMENDMENT OF THE SCHEDULE</b>\n\n
    7. Amendment of the Schedule.—(1) Parliament may from time to time by law amend by way
    of addition, variation or repeal any of the provisions of this Schedule and, when the Schedule is so
    amended, any reference to this Schedule in this Constitution shall be construed as a reference to
    such Schedule as so amended.\n\n
    (2) No such law as is mentioned in sub-paragraph (1) of this paragraph shall be deemed to be an
    amendment of this Constitution for the purposes of article 368.\n\n</string>

<string name="sixthschedule">
<b>SIXTH SCHEDULE</b>\n
    [Articles 244(2) and 275(1)]\n\n
    Provisions as to the Administration of Tribal Areas in the States of Assam,
    Meghalaya, Tripura and Mizoram\n\n
    1. Autonomous districts and autonomous regions.—(1) Subject to the provisions of this
    paragraph, the tribal areas in each item of Parts I, II and IIA and in Part III of the table appended
    to paragraph 20 of this Schedule shall be an autonomous district.\n\n
    (2) If there are different Scheduled Tribes in an autonomous district, the Governor may, by
    public notification, divide the area or areas inhabited by them into autonomous regions.\n\n
    (3) The Governor may, by public notification,—\n\n
    (a) include any area in any of the Parts of the said table,\n
    (b) exclude any area from any of the Parts of the said table,\n
    (c) create a new autonomous district,\n
    (d) increase the area of any autonomous district,\n
    (e) diminish the area of any autonomous district,\n
    (f) unite two or more autonomous districts or parts thereof so as to form one autonomous
    district,\n
    (ff) alter the name of any autonomous district,\n
    (g) define the boundaries of any autonomous district:\n
    Provided that no order shall be made by the Governor under clauses (c), (d), (e) and (f) of this
    sub-paragraph except after consideration of the report of a Commission appointed under subparagraph
    (1) of paragraph 14 of this Schedule:
    Provided further that any order made by the Governor under this sub-paragraph may contain
    such incidental and consequential provisions (including any amendment of paragraph 20 and of
    any item in any of the Parts of the said table) as appear to the Governor to be necessary for giving
    effect to the provisions of the order.\n\n
    2. Constitution of District Councils and Regional Councils.—\n\n
    (1) There shall be a
    District Council for each autonomous district consisting of not more than thirty members,
    of whom not more than four persons shall be nominated by the Governor and the rest shall be
    elected on the basis of adult suffrage.\n\n
    (2) There shall be a separate Regional Council for each area constituted an autonomous region
    under sub-paragraph (2) of paragraph 1 of this Schedule.\n\n
    (3) Each District Council and each Regional Council shall be a body corporate by the name
    respectively of “the District Council of (name of district)" and “the Regional Council of (name of
    region)", shall have perpetual succession and a common seal and shall by the said name sue and
    be sued.\n\n
    (4) Subject to the provisions of this Schedule, the administration of an autonomous district shall,
    in so far as it is not vested under this Schedule in any Regional Council within such district, be
    vested in the District Council for such district and the administration of an autonomous region
    shall be vested in the Regional Council for such region.\n\n
    (5) In an autonomous district with Regional Councils, the District Council shall have only such
    powers with respect to the areas under the authority of the Regional Council as may be delegated
    to it by the Regional Council in addition to the powers conferred on it by this Schedule with
    respect to such areas.\n\n
    (6) The Governor shall make rules for the first constitution of District Councils and Regional
    Councils in consultation with the existing tribal Councils or other representative tribal
    organisations within the autonomous districts or regions concerned, and such rules shall provide
    for—\n\n
    (a) the composition of the District Councils and Regional Councils and the allocation of seats
    therein;\n
    (b) the delimitation of territorial constituencies for the purpose of elections to those Councils;\n
    (c) the qualifications for voting at such elections and the preparation of electoral rolls
    therefor;\n
    (d) the qualifications for being elected at such elections as members of such Councils;\n
    (e) the term of office of members of Regional Councils;\n
    (f) any other matter relating to or connected with elections or nominations to such Councils;\n
    (g) the procedure and the conduct of business (including the power to act notwithstanding
    any vacancy) in the District and Regional Councils;\n
    (h) the appointment of officers and staff of the District and Regional Councils.\n\n
    (6A) The elected members of the District Council shall hold office for a term of five years from
    the date appointed for the first meeting of the Council after the general elections to the Council,
    unless the District Council is sooner dissolved under paragraph 16 and a nominated member shall
    hold office at the pleasure of the Governor:\n\n
    Provided that the said period of five years may, while a Proclamation of Emergency is in
    operation or if circumstances exist which, in the opinion of the Governor, render the holding of
    elections impracticable, be extended by the Governor for a period not exceeding one year at a time
    and in any case where a Proclamation of Emergency is in operation not extending beyond a period
    of six months after the Proclamation has ceased to operate:
    Provided further that a member elected to fill a casual vacancy shall hold office only for the
    remainder of the term of office of the member whom he replaces.\n\n

    (7) The District or the Regional Council may after its first constitution make rules with the
    approval of the Governor with regard to the matters specified in sub-paragraph (6) of this
    paragraph and may also make rules with like approval regulating—\n\n
    (a) the formation of subordinate local Councils or Boards and their procedure
    and the conduct of their business; and\n\n
    (b) generally all matters relating to the transaction of business pertaining to the
    administration of the district or region, as the case may be:\n\n
    Provided that until rules are made by the District or the Regional Council under this subparagraph
    the rules made by the Governor under sub-paragraph (6) of this paragraph shall have
    effect in respect of elections to, the officers and staff of, and the procedure and the conduct of
    business in, each such Council.\n\n
    * * * * *
    3. Powers of the District Councils and Regional Councils to make laws.—\n\n
    (1) The Regional
    Council for an autonomous region in respect of all areas within such region and
    _________________________________________________________________
    *1. Paragraph 3 has been amended in its application to the State of Assam by the Sixth
    Schedule to the Constitution (Amendment) Act, 2003 (44 of 2003), s. 2 , so as to
    substitute sub-paragraph (3) as under, -\n\n
    “(3) Save as otherwise provided in sub-paragraph (2) of paragraph 3A or subparagraph
    (2) of paragraph 3B , all laws made under this paragraph or sub-paragraph
    (1) of paragraph 3A or sub-paragraph (1) of paragraph 3B shall be submitted forthwith
    to the Governor and, until assented to by him, shall have no effect."\n
    After paragraph 3, the following paragraph has been inserted in its application to the State of
    Assam by the Sixth Schedule to the Constitution (Amendment) Act, 1995 (42 of 1995), s.2 ,
    namely:—\n\n
    “3A. Additional powers of the North Cachar Hills Autonomous Council and the Karbi
    Anglong Autonomous Council to make laws.—\n\n
    (1) Without prejudice to the provisions of
    paragraph 3, the North Cachar Hills Autonomous Council and the Karbi Anglong Autonomous
    Council within their respective districts, shall have power to make laws with respect to—\n\n
    (a) industries, subject to the provisions of entries 7 and 52 of List I of the
    Seventh Schedule;\n\n
    (b) communications, that is to say, roads, bridges, ferries and other means of
    communication not specified in List I of the Seventh Schedule; municipal
    tramways, ropeways, inland waterways and traffic thereon subject to the
    provisions of List I and List III of the Seventh Schedule with regard to such
    waterways; vehicles other than mechanically propelled vehicles;\n\n
    (c) preservation, protection and improvement of stock and prevention of
    animal diseases; veterinary training and practice; cattle pounds;\n\n
    (d) primary and secondary education;\n\n
    (e) agriculture, including agricultural education and research, protection
    against pests and prevention of plant diseases;\n\n
    (f) fisheries;\n\n
    (g) water, that is to say, water supplies, irrigation and canals, drainage and
    embankments, water storage and water power subject to the provisions of entry 56
    of List I of the Seventh Schedule;\n\n
    (h) social security and social insurance; employment and unemployment;\n\n
    (i) flood control schemes for protection of villages, paddy fields, markets,
    towns, etc. (not of technical nature);\n\n
    (j) theatre and dramatic performances, cinemas subject to the provisions of
    entry 60 of List I of the Seventh Schedule; sports entertainments and amusements;\n\n
    (k) public health and sanitation, hospitals and dispensaries;\n\n
    (l) minor irrigation;\n\n
    (m) trade and commerce in, and the production supply and distribution of, food stuffs,
    cattle fodder, raw cotton and raw jute;\n\n
    (n) libraries, museums and other similar Institutions controlled or financed by the State;
    ancient and historical monuments and records other than those declared by or under any law
    made by Parliament to be of national importance; and\n\n
    (o) alienation of land.\n\n
    (2) All laws made by the North Cachar Hills Autonomous Council and the Karbi Anglong
    Autonomous Council under paragraph 3 or under this paragraph shall, in so far as they relate to
    matters specified in List III of the Seventh Schedule, be submitted forthwith to the Governor who
    shall reserve the same for the consideration of the President\n\n.
    (3) When a law is reserved for the consideration of the President, the President shall declare
    either that he assents to the said law or that he withholds assent therefrom:
    Provided that the President may direct the Governor to return the law to the North Cachar Hills
    Autonomous Council or the Karbi Anglong Autonomous Council, as the case may be, together
    with a message requesting that the said Council will reconsider the law or any specified provisions
    thereof and, in particular, will, consider the desirability of introducing any such amendments as he
    may recommend in his message and, when the law is so returned, the said Council shall
    consider the law accordingly within a period of six months from the date of receipt of such
    message and, if the law is again passed by the said Council with or without amendment it shall be
    presented again to the President for his consideration.".\n\n
    *After paragraph 3A, the following paragraph has been inserted in its application to the
    State of Assam by the Sixth Schedule to the Constitution (Amendment) Act, 2003, (44
    0f 2003), s. 2 , namely: —\n\n
    “3B. Additional powers of the Bodoland Territorial Council to make laws.—\n\n
    (1) Without prejudice to the provisions of paragraph 3, the Bodoland Territorial Council
    within its areas shall have power to make laws with respect to :- \n(i) Agriculture, including
    agricultural education and research, protection against pests and prevention of plant
    diseases;\n (ii) Animal husbandry and veterinary, that is to say, preservation, protection
    and improvement of stock and prevention of animal diseases, veterinary training and
    practice, cattle pounds;\n (iii) Co-operation;\n (iv) Cultural affairs; \n(v) Education, that is to
    say, primary education, higher secondary including vocational training, adult education,
    college education (general);\n (vi) Fisheries; \n(vii) Flood control for protection of village,
    paddy fields, markets and towns (not of technical nature); \n(viii) Food and civil supply;\n
    (ix) Forests (other than reserved forests); \n(x) Handloom and textile; \n(xi) Health and
    family welfare, \n(xii) Intoxicating liquors, opium and derivatives, subject to the provisions
    of entry 84 of List I of the Seventh Schedule; \n(xiii) Irrigation;\n (xiv) Labour and
    employment;\n (xv) Land and Revenue; \n(xvi) Library services (financed and controlled by
    the State Government); \n(xvii) Lotteries (subject to the provisions of entry 40 of List I of
    the Seventh Schedule), theatres, dramatic performances and cinemas (subject to the
    provisions of entry 60 of List I of the Seventh Schedule); \n(xviii) Markets and fairs; \n(xix) Municipal corporation, improvement trust, district boards and other local authorities; \n(xx)Museum and archaeology institutions controlled or financed by the State, ancient and historical monuments and records other than those declared by or under any law madeby Parliament to be of national importance;\n (xxi) Panchayat and rural development;\n
    (xxii) Planning and development;\n (xxiii) Printing and stationery;\n (xxiv) Pubic health
    engineering; \n(xxv) Public works department;\n (xxvi) Publicity and public relations; \n(xxvii)
    Registration of births and deaths; \n(xxviii) Relief and rehabilitation;\n (xxix) Sericulture;\n
    (xxx) Small, cottage and rural industry subject to the provisions of entries 7 and 52 of
    List I of the Seventh Schedule; \n(xxxi) Social Welfare; \n(xxxii) Soil conservation;\n (xxxiii)
    Sports and youth welfare;\n (xxxiv) Statistics;\n (xxxv) Tourism;\n (xxxvi) Transport (roads,
    bridges, ferries and other means of communications not specified in List I of the
    Seventh Schedule, municipal tramways, ropeways, inland waterways and traffic
    thereon subject to the provision of List I and List III of the Seventh Schedule with regard
    to such waterways, vehicles other than mechanically propelled vehicles);\n (xxxvii) Tribal
    research institute controlled and financed by the State Government;\n (xxxviii) Urban
    development—town and country planning;\n (xxxix) Weights and measures subject to
    the provisions of entry 50 of List I of the Seventh Schedule; and\n (xl) Welfare of plain
    tribes and backward classes:
    Provided that nothing in such laws shall--\n\n
    (a) extinguish or modify the existing rights and privileges of any citizen in respect
    of his land at the date of commencement of this Act; and\n\n
    (b) disallow and citizen from acquiring land either by way of inheritance,
    allotment, settlement or by any other way of transfer if such citizen is otherwise
    eligible for such acquisition of land within the Bodoland Territorial Areas District.\n\n
    (2) All laws made under paragraph 3 or under this paragraph shall in so far as they
    relate to matters specified in List III of the Seventh Schedule, be submitted forthwith to
    the Governor who shall reserve the same for the consideration of the President.\n\n
    (3) When a law is reserved for the consideration of the President, the President shall
    declare either that he assents to the said law or that he withholds assent therefrom:
    Provided that the President may direct the Governor to return the law to the
    Bodoland Territorial Council, together with the message requesting that the said Council
    will reconsider the law or any specified provisions thereof and, in particular, will consider
    the desirability of introducing any such amendments as he may recommend in his
    message and, when the law is so returned, the said Council shall consider the law
    accordingly within a period of six month from the date of receipt of such message and, if
    the law is again passéd by the said Council with or without amendments it shall be
    presented again to the President for his consideration."
    the District Council for an autonomous district in respect of all areas within the district except
    those which are under the authority of Regional Councils, if any, within the district shall have
    power to make laws with respect to—\n\n
    (a) the allotment, occupation or use, or the setting apart, of land, other than
    any land which is a reserved forest for the purposes of agriculture or grazing or for
    residential or other non-agricultural purposes or for any other purpose likely to
    promote the interests of the inhabitants of any village or town:
    Provided that nothing in such laws shall prevent the compulsory acquisition of
    any land, whether occupied or unoccupied, for public purposes by the Government
    of the State concerned in accordance with the law for the time being in force
    authorising such acquisition;\n\n
    (b) the management of any forest not being a reserved forest;\n
    (c) the use of any canal or water-course for the purpose of agriculture;\n
    (d) the regulation of the practice of jhum or other forms of shifting cultivation;\n
    (e) the establishment of village or town committees or councils and their powers;\n
    (f) any other matter relating to village or town administration, including village
    or town police and public health and sanitation;\n
    (g) the appointment or succession of Chiefs or Headmen;\n
    (h) the inheritance of property;\n
    (i) marriage and divorce;\n
    (j) social customs.\n\n
    (2) In this paragraph, a “reserved forest" means any area which is a reserved forest under the
    Assam Forest Regulation, 1891, or under any other law for the time being in force in the area in
    question.\n\n
    (3) All laws made under this paragraph shall be submitted forthwith to the Governor and, until
    assented to by him, shall have no effect.\n\n
    4. Administration of justice in autonomous districts and autonomous regions.—\n\n
    (1) The
    Regional Council for an autonomous region in respect of areas within such region and the District
    Council for an autonomous district in respect of areas within the district other than those which are
    under the authority of the Regional Councils, if any, within the district may constitute village
    councils or courts for the trial of suits and cases between the parties all of whom
    belong to Scheduled Tribes within such areas, other than suits and cases to which the provisions
    of sub-paragraph (1) of paragraph 5 of this Schedule apply, to
    the exclusion of any court in the State, and may appoint suitable persons to be members of such
    village councils or presiding officers of such courts, and may also appoint such officers as may be
    necessary for the administration of the laws made under paragraph 3 of this Schedule.\n\n
    (2) Notwithstanding anything in this Constitution, the Regional Council for an autonomous
    region or any court constituted in that behalf by the Regional Council or, if in respect of any area
    within an autonomous district there is no Regional Council, the District Council for such district,
    or any court constituted in that behalf by the District Council, shall exercise the powers of a court
    of appeal in respect of all suits and cases triable by a village council or court constituted under
    sub-paragraph (1) of this paragraph within such region or area, as the case may be, other than\n\n
    those to which the provisions of sub-paragraph (1) of paragraph 5 of this Schedule apply, and no
    other court except the High Court and the Supreme Court shall have jurisdiction over such suits or
    cases.\n\n
    (3) The High Court shall have and exercise such jurisdiction over the suits and cases to which
    the provisions of sub-paragraph (2) of this paragraph apply as the Governor may from time to time
    by order specify.\n\n
    (4) A Regional Council or District Council, as the case may be, may with the previous approval
    of the Governor make rules regulating —\n\n
    (a) the constitution of village councils and courts and the powers to be exercised
    by them under this paragraph;\n\n
    (b) the procedure to be followed by village councils or courts in the trial of suits
    and cases under sub-paragraph (1) of this paragraph;\n\n
    (c) the procedure to be followed by the Regional or District Council or any court
    constituted by such Council in appeals and other proceedings under sub-paragraph
    (2) of this paragraph;\n\n
    (d) the enforcement of decisions and orders of such councils and courts;\n\n
    (e) all other ancillary matters for the carrying out of the provisions of subparagraphs
    (1) and (2) of this paragraph.\n\n
    (5) On and from such date as the President may, after consulting the Government of the State
    concerned, by notification appoint in this behalf, this paragraph shall have effect in relation to
    such autonomous district or region as may be specified in the notification, as if—\n\n
    (i) in sub-paragraph (1), for the words “between the parties all of whom belong
    to Scheduled Tribes within such areas, other than suits and cases to which the
    provisions of sub-paragraph (1) of paragraph 5 of this Schedule apply,", the words
    “not being suits and cases of the nature referred to in sub-paragraph (1) of
    paragraph (5) of this Schedule, which the Governor may specify in this behalf,"
    had been substituted;\n\n
    (ii) sub-paragraphs (2) and (3) had been omitted;\n\n
    (iii) in sub-paragraph (4)—\n\n
    (a) for the words “A Regional Council or District Council, as the case may
    be, may with the previous approval of the Governor make rules regulating", the
    words “the Governor may make rules regulating" had been substituted; and\n\n
    (b) for clause (a), the following clause had been substituted, namely:—\n\n
    “(a) the constitution of village councils and courts, the powers to be
    exercised by them under this paragraph and the courts to which appeals from
    the decisions of village councils and courts shall lie;";\n\n
    (c) for clause (c), the following clause had been substituted, namely:—\n\n
    “(c) the transfer of appeals and other proceedings pending before the
    Regional or District Council or any court constituted by such Council
    immediately before the date appointed by the President under sub-paragraph
    (5);"; and\n\n
    (d) in clause (e), for the words, brackets and figures “sub-paragraphs (1) and
    (2)", the word, brackets and figure “sub-paragraph (1)" had been substituted.\n\n
<b>5. Conferment of powers under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, and the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898,on the Regional and District Councils and on certain courts and officers for the trial of certain suits, cases and offences.—</b>\n\n
    (1) The Governor may, for the trial of
    suits or cases arising out of any law in force in any autonomous district or region being a law
    specified in that behalf by the Governor, or for the trial of offences punishable with death,
    transportation for life, or imprisonment for a term of not less than five years under the Indian
    Penal Code or under any other law for the time being applicable to such district or region, confer
    on the District Council or the Regional Council having authority over such district or region or on
    courts constituted by such District Council or on any officer appointed in that behalf by the
    Governor, such powers under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, or, as the case may be, the Code
    of Criminal Procedure, 1898
    , as he deems appropriate, and thereupon the said Council, court or
    officer shall try the suits, cases or offences in exercise of the powers so conferred.\n\n
    (2) The Governor may withdraw or modify any of the powers conferred on a District Council,
    Regional Council, court or officer under sub-paragraph (1) of this paragraph.\n\n
    (3) Save as expressly provided in this paragraph, the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, and the
    Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898
    , shall not apply to the trial of any suits, cases or offences in an
    autonomous district or in any autonomous region to which the provisions of this paragraph apply.\n\n
    (4) On and from the date appointed by the President under sub-paragraph (5) of paragraph 4 in
    relation to any autonomous district or autonomous region, nothing contained in this paragraph
    shall, in its application to that district or region, be deemed to authorise the Governor to confer on
    the District Council or Regional Council or on courts constituted by the District Council any of
    the powers referred to in sub-paragraph (1) of this paragraph.\n\n
<b>6. Powers of the District Council to establish primary schools, etc.—</b>\n\n (1) The District
    Council for an autonomous district may establish, construct, or manage primary schools,
    dispensaries, markets, cattle pounds, ferries, fisheries, roads, road transport and waterways in the
    district and may, with the previous approval of the Governor, make regulations for the regulation
    and control thereof and, in particular, may prescribe the language and the manner in which
    primary education shall be imparted in the primary schools in the district.\n\n
    (2) The Governor may, with the consent of any District Council, entrust either conditionally or
    unconditionally to that Council or to its officers functions in relation to agriculture, animal
    husbandry, community projects, co-operative societies, social welfare, village planning or any
    other matter to which the executive power of the State extends.\n\n
<b>7. District and Regional Funds.—</b>\n\n
    (1) There shall be constituted for each autonomous district, a
    District Fund and for each autonomous region, a Regional Fund to which shall be credited all
    moneys received respectively by the District Council for that district and the Regional Council for
    that region in the course of the administration of such district or region, as the case may be, in
    accordance with the provisions of this Constitution.\n\n
    (2) The Governor may make rules for the management of the District Fund, or, as the case may
    be, the Regional Fund and for the procedure to be followed in respect of payment of money into
    the said Fund, the withdrawal of moneys therefrom, the custody of moneys therein and any other
    matter connected with or ancillary to the matters aforesaid.\n\n
    (3) The accounts of the District Council or, as the case may be, the Regional Council shall be
    kept in such form as the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India may, with the approval of the
    President, prescribe.\n\n
    (4) The Comptroller and Auditor-General shall cause the accounts of the District and Regional
    Councils to be audited in such manner as he may think fit, and the reports of the Comptroller and
    Auditor-General relating to such accounts shall be submitted to the Governor who shall cause
    them to be laid before the Council.\n\n
<b>8. Powers to assess and collect land revenue and to impose taxes.—</b>\n\n
    (1) The Regional Council
    for an autonomous region in respect of all lands within such region and the District Council for an
    autonomous district in respect of all lands within the district except those which are in the areas
    under the authority of Regional Councils, if any, within the district, shall have the power to assess
    and collect revenue in respect of such lands in accordance with the principles for the time being
    followed by the Government of the State in assessing lands for the purpose of land revenue in the
    State generally.\n\n
    (2) The Regional Council for an autonomous region in respect of areas within such region and
    the District Council for an autonomous district in respect of all areas in the district except those
    which are under the authority of Regional Councils, if any, within the district, shall have power to
    levy and collect taxes on lands and buildings, and tolls on persons resident within such areas.\n\n
    (3) The District Council for an autonomous district shall have the power to levy and collect all
    or any of the following taxes within such district, that is to say —\n\n
    (a) taxes on professions, trades, callings and employments;\n
    (b) taxes on animals, vehicles and boats;\n
    (c) taxes on the entry of goods into a market for sale therein, and tolls on
    passengers and goods carried in ferries; and\n
    (d) taxes for the maintenance of schools, dispensaries or roads.\n
    (4) A Regional Council or District Council, as the case may be, may make regulations to provide
    for the levy and collection of any of the taxes specified in sub-paragraphs (2) and (3) of this
    paragraph and every such regulation shall be submitted forthwith to the Governor and, until
    assented to by him, shall have no effect./n/n
<b>9. Licences or leases for the purpose of prospecting for, or extraction of, minerals.—</b>\n\n
    (1)
    Such share of the royalties accruing each year from licences or leases for the purpose of
    prospecting for, or the extraction of, minerals granted by the Government of the State in respect of
    any area within an autonomous district as may be agreed upon between the Government of the
    State and the District Council of such district shall be made over to that District Council.\n\n
    (2) If any dispute arises as to the share of such royalties to be made over to a District Council, it
    shall be referred to the Governor for determination and the amount determined by the Governor in
    his discretion shall be deemed to be the amount payable under sub-paragraph (1) of this paragraph
    to the District Council and the decision of the Governor shall be final.\n\n
<b>10. Power of District Council to make regulations for the control of money-lending and
trading by non-tribals.—</b>\n\n
    (1) The District Council of an autonomous district may make
    regulations for the regulation and control of money-lending or trading within the district by
    persons other than Scheduled Tribes resident in the district.\n\n
    (2) In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such regulations
    may—\n\n
    (a) prescribe that no one except the holder of a licence issued in that behalf shall
    carry on the business of money-lending;\n
    (b) prescribe the maximum rate of interest which may be charged or be recovered by a
    money-lender;\n
    (c) provide for the maintenance of accounts by money-lenders and for the inspection of such
    accounts by officers appointed in that behalf by the District Council;\n
    (d) prescribe that no person who is not a member of the Scheduled Tribes resident in the
    district shall carry on wholesale or retail business in any commodity except under a licence
    issued in that behalf by the District Council :\n\n
    Provided that no regulations may be made under this paragraph unless they are passed by a
    majority of not less than three-fourths of the total membership of the District Council:
    Provided further that it shall not be competent under any such regulations to refuse the grant of a
    licence to a money-lender or a trader who has been carrying on business within the district since
    before the time of the making of such regulations.\n\n
    (3) All regulations made under this paragraph shall be submitted forthwith to the Governor and,
    until assented to by him, shall have no effect.\n\n
<b>11. Publication of laws, rules and regulations made under the Schedule.—</b>\n\n
    All laws, rules
    and regulations made under this Schedule by a District Council or a Regional Council shall be
    published forthwith in the Official Gazette of the State and shall on such publication have the
    force of law.\n\n
<b>12. Application of Acts of Parliament and of the Legislature of the State of Assam to
autonomous districts and autonomous regions in the State of Assam. —</b>
    (1) Notwithstanding
    anything in this Constitution —\n\n
    (a) no Act of the Legislature of the State of Assam in respect of any of the matters specified
    in paragraph 3 of this Schedule as matters with respect to which a District Council or a Regional
    Council may make laws, and no Act of the Legislature of the State of Assam prohibiting or
    restricting the consumption of any non-distilled alcoholic liquor shall apply to any autonomous
    district or autonomous region in that State unless in either case the District Council for such
    district or having jurisdiction over such region by public notification so directs, and the District
    Council in giving such direction with respect to any Act may direct that the Act shall in its
    application to such district or region or any part thereof have effect subject to such exceptions or
    modifications as it thinks fit;\n\n
    (b) the Governor may, by public notification, direct that any Act of Parliament or of the
    Legislature of the State of Assam to which the provisions of clause (a) of this sub-paragraph do
    not apply shall not apply to an autonomous district or an autonomous region in that State, or
    shall apply to such district or region or any part thereof subject to such exceptions or
    modifications as he may specify in the notification.\n\n
    (2) Any direction given under sub-paragraph (1) of this paragraph may be given so as to have
    retrospective effect.\n\n
<b>12A. Application of Acts of Parliament and of the Legislature of the State of Meghalaya to
autonomous districts and autonomous regions in the State of Meghalaya.—</b>\n\n
    Notwithstanding
    anything in this Constitution,—\n\n
    (a) if any provision of a law made by a District or Regional Council in the State
    of Meghalaya with respect to any matter specified in sub-paragraph (1) of
    paragraph 3 of this Schedule or if any provision of any regulation made by a
    District Council or a Regional Council in that State under paragraph 8 or paragraph
    10 of this Schedule, is repugnant to any provision of a law made by the Legislature
    of the State of Meghalaya with respect to that matter, then, the law or regulation
    made by the District Council or, as the case may be, the Regional Council whether
    made before
    or after the law made by the Legislature of the State of Meghalaya, shall, to the
    extent of repugnancy, be void and the law made by the Legislature of the State of
    Meghalaya shall prevail;
    (b) the President may, with respect to any Act of Parliament, by notification,
    direct that it shall not apply to an autonomous district or an autonomous region in
    the State of Meghalaya, or shall apply to such district or region or any part thereof
    subject to such exceptions or modifications as he may specify in the notification
    and any such direction may be given so as to have retrospective effect.\n\n
<b>12AA. Application of Acts of Parliament and of the Legislature of the State of Tripura to
the autonomous districts and autonomous regions in the State of Tripura.—</b>\n\n
    otwithstanding
    anything in this Constitution,—\n\n
    (a) no Act of the Legislature of the State of Tripura in respect of any of the
    matters specified in paragraph 3 of this Schedule as matters with respect to which a
    District Council or a Regional Council may make laws, and no Act of the
    Legislature of the State of Tripura prohibiting or restricting the consumption of any
    non-distilled alcoholic liquor shall apply to the autonomous district or an
    autonomous region in that State unless, in either case, the District Council for that
    district or having jurisdiction over such region by public notification so directs,
    and the District Council in giving such direction with respect to any Act may direct
    that the Act shall, in its application to that district or such region or any part
    thereof, have effect subject to such exceptions or modifications as it thinks fit;\n\n
    (b) the Governor may, by public notification, direct that any Act of the
    Legislature of the State of Tripura to which the provisions of clause (a) of this subparagraph
    do not apply, shall not apply to the autonomous district or any
    autonomous region in that State, or shall apply to that district or such region, or
    any part thereof, subject to such exceptions or modifications, as he may specify in
    the notification;\n\n
    (c) the President may, with respect to any Act of Parliament, by notification,
    direct that it shall not apply to the autonomous district or an autonomous region in
    the State of Tripura, or shall apply to such district or region or any part thereof,
    subject to such exceptions or modifications as he may specify in the notification
    and any such direction may be given so as to have retrospective effect.\n\n
<b>12B. Application of Acts of Parliament and of the Legislature of the State of Mizoram to
autonomous districts and autonomous regions in the State of Mizoram.—</b>\n\n
    Notwithstanding
    anything in this Constitution, —\n\n
    (a) no Act of the Legislature of the State of Mizoram in respect of any of the
    matters specified in paragraph 3 of this Schedule as matters with respect to which a
    District Council or a Regional Council may make laws, and no Act of the
    Legislature of the State of Mizoram prohibiting or restricting the consumption of
    any non-distilled alcoholic liquor shall apply to any autonomous district or
    autonomous region in that State unless, in either case, the District Council for such
    district or having jurisdiction over such region, by public notification, so directs,
    and the District Council, in giving such direction with respect to any Act, may
    direct that the Act shall, in its application to such district or region or any part
    thereof, have effect subject to such exceptions or modifications as it thinks fit;\n\n
    (b) the Governor may, by public notification, direct that any Act of the
    Legislature of the State of Mizoram to which the provisions of clause (a) of this
    sub-paragraph do not apply, shall not apply to an autonomous district or an
    autonomous region in that State, or shall apply to such district or region, or any
    part thereof, subject to such exceptions or modifications, as he may specify in the
    notification;\n\n
    (c) the President may, with respect to any Act of Parliament, by notification,
    direct that it shall not apply to an autonomous district or an autonomous region in
    the State of Mizoram, or shall apply to such district or region or any part thereof,
    subject to such exceptions or modifications as he may specify in the notification
    and any such direction may be given so as to have retrospective effect.\n\n
<b>13. Estimated receipts and expenditure pertaining to autonomous districts to be shown
separately in the annual financial statement.—</b>\n\n
    The estimated receipts and expenditure
    pertaining to an autonomous district which are to be credited to, or is to be made from, the
    Consolidated Fund of the State shall be first placed before the District Council for discussion and
    then after such discussion be shown separately in the annual financial statement of the State to be
    laid before the Legislature of the State under article 202.\n\n
<b>14. Appointment of Commission to inquire into and report on the administration of
autonomous districts and autonomous regions.—</b>\n\n
    (1) The Governor may at any time appoint a
    Commission to examine and report on any matter specified by him relating to the administration
    of the autonomous districts and autonomous regions in the State, including matters specified in
    clauses (c), (d), (e) and (f) of sub-paragraph (3) of paragraph 1 of this Schedule, or may appoint a
    Commission to inquire into and report from time to time on the administration of autonomous
    districts and autonomous regions in the State generally and in particular on—\n\n
    (a) the provision of educational and medical facilities and communications in
    such districts and regions;\n\n
    (b) the need for any new or special legislation in respect of such districts and
    regions; and\n\n
    (c) the administration of the laws, rules and regulations made by the District and
    Regional Councils;\n
    and define the procedure to be followed by such Commission.\n\n
    (2) The report of every such Commission with the recommendations of the Governor with
    respect thereto shall be laid before the Legislature of the State by the Minister concerned together
    with an explanatory memorandum regarding the action proposed to be taken thereon by the
    Government of the State.\n\n
    (3) In allocating the business of the Government of the State among his Ministers the Governor
    may place one of his Ministers specially in charge of the welfare of the autonomous districts and
    autonomous regions in the State.\n\n
<b>15. Annulment or suspension of acts and resolutions of District and Regional Councils.—</b>\n\n
    (1) If at any time the Governor is satisfied that an act or resolution of a District or a Regional
    Council is likely to endanger the safety of India or is likely to be prejudicial to public order, he
    may annul or suspend such act or resolution and take such steps as he may consider necessary
    (including the suspension of the Council and the assumption to himself of all or any of the powers
    vested in or exercisable by the Council) to prevent the commission or continuance of such act, or
    the giving of effect to such resolution.\n\n
    (2) Any order made by the Governor under sub-paragraph (1) of this paragraph together with the
    reasons therefor shall be laid before the Legislature of the State as soon as possible and the order
    shall, unless revoked by the Legislature of the State, continue in force for a period of twelve
    months from the date on which it was so made:
    Provided that if and so often as a resolution approving the continuance in force of such order is
    passed by the Legislature of the State, the order shall unless cancelled by the Governor continue in
    force for a further period of twelve months from the date on which under this paragraph it would
    otherwise have ceased to operate.\n\n
<b>16. Dissolution of a District or a Regional Council.—</b>\n\n
    (1) The Governor may on the
    recommendation of a Commission appointed under paragraph 14 of this Schedule by public
    notification order the dissolution of a District or a Regional Council, and—\n\n
    (a) direct that a fresh general election shall be held immediately for the
    reconstitution of the Council, or\n\n
    (b) subject to the previous approval of the Legislature of the State assume the
    administration of the area under the authority of such Council himself or place the
    administration of such area under the Commission appointed under the said
    paragraph or any other body considered suitable by him for a period not exceeding
    twelve months:
    Provided that when an order under clause (a) of this paragraph has been made, the Governor
    may take the action referred to in clause (b) of this paragraph with regard to the administration of
    the area in question pending the reconstitution of the Council on fresh general election:
    Provided further that no action shall be taken under clause (b) of this paragraph without giving
    the District or the Regional Council, as the case may be, an opportunity of placing its views before
    the Legislature of the State.\n\n
    (2) If at any time the Governor is satisfied that a situation has arisen in which the administration
    of an autonomous district or region cannot be carried on in accordance with the provisions of this
    Schedule, he may, by public notification, assume to himself all or any of the functions or powers
    vested in or exercisable by the District Council or, as the case may be, the Regional Council and
    declare that such functions or powers shall be exercisable by such person or authority as he may
    specify in this behalf, for a period not exceeding six months:\n
    Provided that the Governor may by a further order or orders extend the operation of the initial
    order by a period not exceeding six months on each occasion.\n\n
    (3) Every order made under sub-paragraph (2) of this paragraph with the reasons therefor shall
    be laid before the Legislature of the State and shall cease to operate at the expiration of thirty days
    from the date on which the State Legislature first sits after the issue of the order, unless, before the
    expiry of that period it has been approved by that State Legislature.\n\n
<b>17. Exclusion of areas from autonomous districts in forming constituencies in such
districts.—</b>\n\n
    For the purposes of elections to the Legislative Assembly of Assam or Meghalaya or
    Tripura or Mizoram, the Governor may by order declare that any area within an autonomous
    district in the State of Assam or Meghalaya or Tripura or Mizoram, as the case may be, shall not
    form part of any constituency to fill a seat or seats in the Assembly reserved for any such district
    but shall form part of a constituency to fill a seat or seats in the Assembly not so reserved to be
    specified in the order.\n\n
    * * * * *
    2
<b>19. Transitional provisions.—</b>\n\n
    (1) As soon as possible after the commencement of this
    Constitution the Governor shall take steps for the constitution of a District Council for each
    autonomous district in the State under this Schedule and, until a District Council is so constituted
    for an autonomous district, the administration of such district shall be vested in the Governor and
    the following provisions shall apply to the administration of the areas within such district instead
    of the foregoing provisions of this Schedule, namely:—\n\n
    (a) no Act of Parliament or of the Legislature of the State shall apply to any such area
    unless the Governor by public notification so directs; and the Governor in giving such a
    direction with respect to any Act may direct that the Act shall, in its application to the area or
    to any specified part thereof, have effect subject to such exceptions or modifications as he
    thinks fit;\n\n
    (b) the Governor may make regulations for the peace and good government
    of any such area and any regulations so made may repeal or amend any Act of
    Parliament or of the Legislature of the State or any existing law which is for the
    time being applicable to such area.\n\n
    (2) Any direction given by the Governor under clause (a) of sub-paragraph (1) of this paragraph
    may be given so as to have retrospective effect.\n\n
    (3) All regulations made under clause (b) of sub-paragraph (1) of this paragraph shall be
    submitted forthwith to the President and, until assented to by him, shall have no effect.\n\n
<b>20. Tribal areas.—</b>\n\n
    (1) The areas specified in Parts I, II, IIA and III of the table below shall
    respectively be the tribal areas within the State of Assam, the State of Meghalaya, the State of
    Tripura and the State of Mizoram.\n\n
    (2) Any reference in Part I, Part II or Part III of the table below to any district shall be construed
    as a reference to the territories comprised within the autonomous district of that name existing
    immediately before the day appointed under clause (b) of section 2 of the North-Eastern Areas
    (Reorganisation) Act, 1971:\n
    Provided that for the purposes of clauses (e) and (f) of sub-paragraph (1) of paragraph 3,
    paragraph 4, paragraph 5, paragraph 6, sub-paragraph (2), clauses (a), (b) and (d) of sub-paragraph
    (3) and sub-paragraph (4) of paragraph 8 and clause (d) of sub-paragraph (2) of paragraph 10 of
    this Schedule, no part of the area comprised within the municipality of Shillong shall be deemed to
    be within the Khasi Hills District.\n\n
    (3) The reference in Part IIA in the table below to the "Tripura Tribal Areas District" shall be
    construed as a reference to the territory comprising the tribal areas specified in the First Schedule
    to the Tripura Tribal Areas Autonomous District Council Act, 1979.\n\n
<b>TABLE</b>\n
<b>PART I</b>\n\n
    1. The North Cachar Hills District.\n
    2. The Karbi Anglong District.\n
    3. The Bodoland Territorial Areas District.\n\n
<b>PART II</b>\n\n
    1. Khasi Hills District.\n
    2. Jaintia Hills District.\n
    3. The Garo Hills District.\n\n
<b>PART IIA</b>\n\n
    Tripura Tribal Areas District\n\n
<b>PART III</b>\n\n
    1. The Chakma District.\n
    2. The Mara District.\n
    3. The Lai District.\n\n
<b>20A. Dissolution of the Mizo District Council.—</b>\n\n
    (1) Notwithstanding anything in this
    Schedule, the District Council of the Mizo District existing immediately before the prescribed date
    (hereinafter referred to as the Mizo District Council) shall stand dissolved and cease to exist.\n\n
    (2) The Administrator of the Union territory of Mizoram may, by one or more orders, provide
    for all or any of the following matters, namely:—\n\n
    (a) the transfer, in whole or in part, of the assets, rights and liabilities of the
    Mizo District Council (including the rights and liabilities under any contract made
    by it) to the Union or to any other authority;\n\n
    (b) the substitution of the Union or any other authority for the Mizo District
    Council, or the addition of the Union or any other authority, as a party to any legal
    proceedings to which the Mizo District Council is a party;\n\n
    (c) the transfer or re-employment of any employees of the Mizo District Council
    to or by the Union or any other authority, the terms and conditions of service
    applicable to such employees after such transfer or re-employment;\n\n
    (d) the continuance of any laws, made by the Mizo District Council and in force
    immediately before its dissolution, subject to such adaptations and modifications,
    whether by way of repeal or amendment, as the Administrator may make in this
    behalf, until such laws are altered, repealed or amended by a competent Legislature
    or other competent authority;\n\n
    (e) such incidental, consequential and supplementary matters as the
    Administrator considers necessary.\n
    Explanation.—In this paragraph and in paragraph 20B of this Schedule, the expression
    "prescribed date" means the date on which the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory of
    Mizoram is duly constituted under and in accordance with the provisions of the Government of
    Union Territories Act, 1963.\n\n
<b>20B. Autonomous regions in the Union territory of Mizoram to be autonomous districts
and transitory provisions consequent thereto.—</b>\n\n
    (1) Notwithstanding anything in this
    Schedule,—\n\n
    (a) every autonomous region existing immediately before the prescribed date
    in the Union territory of Mizoram shall, on and from that date, be an autonomous
    district in that Union territory (hereafter referred to as the corresponding new
    district) and the Administrator thereof may, by one or more orders, direct that such
    consequential amendments as are necessary to give effect to the provisions of this
    clause shall be made in paragraph 20 of this Schedule (including Part III of the
    table appended to that paragraph) and thereupon the said paragraph and the said
    Part III shall be deemed to have been amended accordingly;\n\n
    (b) every Regional Council of an autonomous region in the Union territory of
    Mizoram existing immediately before the prescribed date (hereafter referred to as
    the existing Regional Council) shall, on and from that date and until a District
    Council is duly constituted for the corresponding new district, be deemed to be the
    District Council of that district (hereafter referred to as the corresponding new
    District Council).\n\n
    (2) Every member whether elected or nominated of an existing Regional Council shall be
    deemed to have been elected or, as the case may be, nominated to the corresponding new District
    Council and shall hold office until a District Council is duly constituted for the corresponding new
    district under this Schedule.\n\n
    (3) Until rules are made under sub-paragraph (7) of paragraph 2 and sub-paragraph (4) of
    paragraph 4 of this Schedule by the corresponding new District Council, the rules made under the
    said provisions by the existing Regional Council and in force immediately before the prescribed
    date shall have effect in relation to the corresponding new District Council subject to such
    adaptations and modifications as may be made therein by the Administrator of the Union territory
    of Mizoram.\n\n
    (4) The Administrator of the Union territory of Mizoram may, by one or more orders, provide
    for all or any of the following matters, namely:—\n\n
    (a) the transfer in whole or in part of the assets, rights and liabilities of the
    existing Regional Council (including the rights and liabilities under any contract
    made by it) to the corresponding new District Council;\n\n
    (b) the substitution of the corresponding new District Council for the existing
    Regional Council as a party to the legal proceedings to which the existing Regional
    Council is a party;\n\n
    (c) the transfer or re-employment of any employees of the existing Regional
    Council to or by the corresponding new District Council, the terms and conditions
    of service applicable to such employees after such transfer or re-employment;\n\n
    (d) the continuance of any laws made by the existing Regional Council and in
    force immediately before the prescribed date, subject to such adaptations and
    modifications, whether by way of repeal or amendment, as the Administrator may
    make in this behalf until such laws are altered, repealed or amended by a competent
    Legislature or other competent authority;\n\n
    (e) such incidental, consequential and supplementary matters as the
    Administrator considers necessary.\n\n
<b>20C. Interpretation.—</b>\n\n
    Subject to any provision made in this behalf, the provisions of this
    Schedule shall, in their application to the Union territory of Mizoram, have effect—\n\n
    (1) as if references to the Governor and Government of the State were
    references to the Administrator of the Union territory appointed under article 239,
    references to State (except in the expression "Government of the State") were
    references to the Union territory of Mizoram and references to the State Legislature
    were references to the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory of Mizoram;\n\n
    (2) as if—\n\n
    (a) in sub-paragraph (5) of paragraph 4, the provision for consultation
    with the Government of the State concerned had been omitted;\n\n
    (b) in sub-paragraph (2) of paragraph 6, for the words "to which the
    executive power of the State extends", the words "with respect to which the
    Legislative Assembly of the Union territory of Mizoram has power to make
    laws" had been substituted;\n\n
    (c) in paragraph 13, the words and figures "under article 202" had been
    omitted.\n\n
<b>21. Amendment of the Schedule.—</b>\n\n
    (1) Parliament may from time to time by law amend by way
    of addition, variation or repeal any of the provisions of this Schedule and, when the Schedule is so
    amended, any reference to this Schedule in this Constitution shall be construed as a reference to
    such Schedule as so amended.\n\n
    (2) No such law as is mentioned in sub-paragraph (1) of this paragraph shall be deemed to be an
    amendment of this Constitution for the purposes of article 368.\n\n</string>
<string name="seventhschedule">
<b>SEVENTH SCHEDULE</b>\n
    (Article 246)\n\n
    List I—Union List\n
    1. Defence of India and every part thereof including preparation for defence and all such acts as
    may be conducive in times of war to its prosecution and after its termination to effective
    demobilisation.\n\n
    2. Naval, military and air forces; any other armed forces of the Union.\n\n
    2A. Deployment of any armed force of the Union or any other force subject to the control of the
    Union or any contingent or unit thereof in any State in aid of the civil power; powers, jurisdiction,
    privileges and liabilities of the members of such forces while on such deployment.\n\n
    3. Delimitation of cantonment areas, local self-government in such areas, the constitution and
    powers within such areas of cantonment authorities and the regulation of house accommodation
    (including the control of rents) in such areas.\n\n
    4. Naval, military and air force works.\n\n
    5. Arms, firearms, ammunition and explosives.\n\n
    6. Atomic energy and mineral resources necessary for its production.\n\n
    7. Industries declared by Parliament by law to be necessary for the purpose of defence or for the
    prosecution of war.\n\n
    8. Central Bureau of Intelligence and Investigation.\n\n
    9. Preventive detention for reasons connected with Defence, Foreign Affairs, or the security of
    India; persons subjected to such detention.\n\n
    10. Foreign affairs; all matters which bring the Union into relation with any foreign country.\n\n
    11. Diplomatic, consular and trade representation.\n\n
    12. United Nations Organisation.\n\n
    13. Participation in international conferences, associations and other bodies and implementing of
    decisions made thereat.\n\n
    14. Entering into treaties and agreements with foreign countries and implementing of treaties,
    agreements and conventions with foreign countries.\n\n
    15. War and peace.\n\n
    16. Foreign jurisdiction.\n\n
    17. Citizenship, naturalisation and aliens.\n\n
    18. Extradition.\n\n
    19. Admission into, and emigration and expulsion from, India; passports and visas.\n\n
    20. Pilgrimages to places outside India.\n\n
    21. Piracies and crimes committed on the high seas or in the air; offences against the law of
    nations committed on land or the high seas or in the air.\n\n
    22. Railways.\n\n
    23. Highways declared by or under law made by Parliament to be national highways.\n\n
    24. Shipping and navigation on inland waterways, declared by Parliament by law to be national
    waterways, as regards mechanically propelled vessels; the rule of the road on such waterways.\n\n
    25. Maritime shipping and navigation, including shipping and navigation on tidal waters;
    provision of education and training for the mercantile marine and regulation of such education and
    training provided by States and other agencies.\n\n
    26. Lighthouses, including lightships, beacons and other provision for the safety of shipping and
    aircraft.\n\n
    27. Ports declared by or under law made by Parliament or existing law to be major ports,
    including their delimitation, and the constitution and powers of port authorities therein.\n\n
    28. Port quarantine, including hospitals connected therewith; seamen\'s and marine hospitals.\n\n
    29. Airways; aircraft and air navigation; provision of aerodromes; regulation and organisation of
    air traffic and of aerodromes; provision for aeronautical education and training and regulation of
    such education and training provided by States and other agencies.\n\n
    30. Carriage of passengers and goods by railway, sea or air, or by national waterways in
    mechanically propelled vessels.\n\n
    31. Posts and telegraphs; telephones, wireless, broadcasting and other like forms of
    communication.\n\n
    32. Property of the Union and the revenue therefrom, but as regards property situated in a State
    subject to legislation by the State, save in so far as Parliament by law otherwise provides.\n\n
    34. Courts of wards for the estates of Rulers of Indian States.\n\n
    35. Public debt of the Union.\n\n
    36. Currency, coinage and legal tender; foreign exchange.\n\n
    37. Foreign loans.\n\n
    38. Reserve Bank of India.\n\n
    39. Post Office Savings Bank.\n\n
    40. Lotteries organised by the Government of India or the Government of a State.\n\n
    41. Trade and commerce with foreign countries; import and export across customs frontiers;
    definition of customs frontiers.\n\n
    42. Inter-State trade and commerce.\n\n
    43. Incorporation, regulation and winding up of trading corporations, including banking,
    insurance and financial corporations, but not including co-operative societies.\n\n
    44. Incorporation, regulation and winding up of corporations, whether trading or not, with
    objects not confined to one State, but not including universities.\n\n
    45. Banking.\n\n
    46. Bills of exchange, cheques, promissory notes and other like instruments.\n\n
    47. Insurance.\n\n
    48. Stock exchanges and futures markets.\n\n
    49. Patents, inventions and designs; copyright; trade-marks and merchandise marks.\n\n
    50. Establishment of standards of weight and measure.\n\n
    51. Establishment of standards of quality for goods to be exported out of India or transported
    from one State to another.\n\n
    52. Industries, the control of which by the Union is declared by Parliament by law to be
    expedient in the public interest.\n\n
    53. Regulation and development of oilfields and mineral oil resources; petroleum and petroleum
    products; other liquids and substances declared by Parliament by law to be dangerously
    inflammable.\n\n
    54. Regulation of mines and mineral development to the extent to which such regulation and
    development under the control of the Union is declared by Parliament by law to be expedient in
    the public interest.\n\n
    55. Regulation of labour and safety in mines and oilfields.\n\n
    56. Regulation and development of inter-State rivers and river valleys to the extent to which
    such regulation and development under the control of the Union is declared by Parliament by law
    to be expedient in the public interest.\n\n
    57. Fishing and fisheries beyond territorial waters.\n\n
    58. Manufacture, supply and distribution of salt by Union agencies; regulation and control of
    manufacture, supply and distribution of salt by other agencies.\n\n
    59. Cultivation, manufacture, and sale for export, of opium.\n\n
    60. Sanctioning of cinematograph films for exhibition.\n\n
    61. Industrial disputes concerning Union employees.\n\n
    62. The institutions known at the commencement of this Constitution as the National Library,
    the Indian Museum, the Imperial War Museum, the Victoria Memorial and the Indian War
    Memorial, and any other like institution financed by the Government of India wholly or in part
    and declared by Parliament by law to be an institution of national importance.\n\n
    63. The institutions known at the commencement of this Constitution as the Benares Hindu
    University, the Aligarh Muslim University and the Delhi University; the University established in
    pursuance of article 371E; any other institution declared by Parliament by law to be an institution
    of national importance.\n\n
    64. Institutions for scientific or technical education financed by the Government of India wholly
    or in part and declared by Parliament by law to be institutions of national importance.\n\n
    65. Union agencies and institutions for—\n
    (a) professional, vocational or technical training, including the training of
    police officers; or\n
    (b) the promotion of special studies or research; or\n
    (c) scientific or technical assistance in the investigation or detection of crime.\n
    66. Co-ordination and determination of standards in institutions for higher education or research
    and scientific and technical institutions.\n\n
    67. Ancient and historical monuments and records, and archaeological sites and remains,
    declared by or under law made by Parliament to be of national importance.\n\n
    68. The Survey of India, the Geological, Botanical, Zoological and Anthropological Surveys of
    India; Meteorological organisations.\n\n
    69. Census.\n\n
    70. Union Public Service; All-India Services; Union Public Service Commission.\n\n
    71. Union pensions, that is to say, pensions payable by the Government of India or out of the
    Consolidated Fund of India.\n\n
    72. Elections to Parliament, to the Legislatures of States and to the offices of President and
    Vice-President; the Election Commission.\n\n
    73. Salaries and allowances of members of Parliament, the Chairman and Deputy Chairman of
    the Council of States and the Speaker and Deputy Speaker of the House of the People.\n\n
    74. Powers, privileges and immunities of each House of Parliament and of the members and the
    Committees of each House; enforcement of attendance of persons for giving evidence or
    producing documents before committees of Parliament or commissions appointed by Parliament.\n\n
    75. Emoluments, allowances, privileges, and rights in respect of leave of absence, of the
    President and Governors; salaries and allowances of the Ministers for the Union; the salaries,
    allowances, and rights in respect of leave of absence and other conditions of service of the
    Comptroller and Auditor-General.\n\n
    76. Audit of the accounts of the Union and of the States.\n\n
    77. Constitution, organisation, jurisdiction and powers of the Supreme Court (including
    contempt of such Court), and the fees taken therein; persons entitled to practise before the
    Supreme Court.\n\n
    78. Constitution and organisation (including vacations) of the High Courts except provisions as
    to officers and servants of High Courts; persons entitled to practise before the High Courts.\n\n
    79. Extension of the jurisdiction of a High Court to, and exclusion of the jurisdiction of a High
    Court from, any Union territory.\n\n
    80. Extension of the powers and jurisdiction of members of a police force belonging to any State
    to any area outside that State, but not so as to enable the police of one State to exercise powers and
    jurisdiction in any area outside that State without the consent of the Government of the State in
    which such area is situated; extension of the powers and jurisdiction of members of a police force
    belonging to any State to railway areas outside that State.\n\n
    81. Inter-State migration; inter-State quarantine.\n\n
    82. Taxes on income other than agricultural income.\n\n
    83. Duties of customs including export duties.\n\n
    84. Duties of excise on tobacco and other goods manufactured or produced in India except—\n\n
    (a) alcoholic liquors for human consumption;\n
    (b) opium, Indian hemp and other narcotic drugs and narcotics,\n
    but including medicinal and toilet preparations containing alcohol or any substance included in
    sub-paragraph (b) of this entry.\n\n
    85. Corporation tax.\n\n
    86. Taxes on the capital value of the assets, exclusive of agricultural land, of individuals and
    companies; taxes on the capital of companies.\n\n
    87. Estate duty in respect of property other than agricultural land.\n\n
    88. Duties in respect of succession to property other than agricultural land.\n\n
    89. Terminal taxes on goods or passengers, carried by railway, sea or air; taxes on railway fares
    and freights.\n\n
    90. Taxes other than stamp duties on transactions in stock exchanges and futures markets.\n\n
    91. Rates of stamp duty in respect of bills of exchange, cheques, promissory notes, bills of
    lading, letters of credit, policies of insurance, transfer of shares, debentures, proxies and receipts.\n\n
    92. Taxes on the sale or purchase of newspapers and on advertisements published therein.\n\n
    92A. Taxes on the sale or purchase of goods other than newspapers, where such sale or purchase
    takes place in the course of inter-State trade or commerce.\n\n
    92B. Taxes on the consignments of goods (whether the consignment is to the person making it
    or to any other person), where such consignment takes place in the course of inter-State trade or
    commerce.\n\n
    93. Offences against laws with respect to any of the matters in this List.\n\n
    94. Inquires, surveys and statistics for the purpose of any of the matters in this List.\n\n
    95. Jurisdiction and powers of all courts, except the Supreme Court, with respect to any of the
    matters in this List; admiralty jurisdiction.\n\n
    96. Fees in respect of any of the matters in this List, but not including fees taken in any court.\n\n
    97. Any other matter not enumerated in List II or List III including any tax not mentioned in
    either of those Lists.\n\n
<b>List II—State List</b>\n\n
    1. Public order (but not including the use of any naval, military or air force or any other armed
    force of the Union or of any other force subject to the control of the Union or of any contingent or
    unit thereof in aid of the civil power).\n\n
    2. Police (including railway and village police) subject to the provisions of entry 2A of List I.\n\n
    3. Officers and servants of the High Court; procedure in rent and revenue courts; fees taken in all
    courts except the Supreme Court.\n\n
    4. Prisons, reformatories, Borstal institutions and other institutions of a like nature, and persons
    detained therein; arrangements with other States for the use of prisons and other institutions.\n\n
    5. Local government, that is to say, the constitution and powers of municipal corporations,
    improvement trusts, districts boards, mining settlement authorities and other local authorities for
    the purpose of local self-government or village administration.\n\n
    6. Public health and sanitation; hospitals and dispensaries.\n\n
    7. Pilgrimages, other than pilgrimages to places outside India.\n\n
    8. Intoxicating liquors, that is to say, the production, manufacture, possession, transport,
    purchase and sale of intoxicating liquors.\n\n
    9. Relief of the disabled and unemployable.\n\n
    10. Burials and burial grounds; cremations and cremation grounds.\n\n
    12. Libraries, museums and other similar institutions controlled or financed by the State; ancient
    and historical monuments and records other than those declared by or under law made by
    Parliament to be of national importance.\n\n
    13. Communications, that is to say, roads, bridges, ferries, and other means of communication
    not specified in List I; municipal tramways; ropeways; inland waterways and traffic thereon
    subject to the provisions of List I and List III with regard to such waterways; vehicles other than
    mechanically propelled vehicles.\n\n
    14. Agriculture, including agricultural education and research, protection against pests and
    prevention of plant diseases.\n\n
    15. Preservation, protection and improvement of stock and prevention of animal diseases;
    veterinary training and practice.\n\n
    16. Pounds and the prevention of cattle trespass.\n\n
    17. Water, that is to say, water supplies, irrigation and canals, drainage and embankments, water
    storage and water power subject to the provisions of entry 56 of List I.\n\n
    18. Land, that is to say, rights in or over land, land tenures including the relation of landlord and
    tenant, and the collection of rents; transfer and alienation of agricultural land; land improvement
    and agricultural loans; colonization.\n\n
    21. Fisheries.\n\n
    22. Courts of wards subject to the provisions of entry 34 of List I; encumbered and attached
    estates.\n\n
    23. Regulation of mines and mineral development subject to the provisions of
    List I with respect to regulation and development under the control of the Union.\n\n
    24. Industries subject to the provisions of entries 7 and 52 of List I.\n\n
    25. Gas and gas-works.\n\n
    26. Trade and commerce within the State subject to the provisions of entry 33 of List III.\n\n
    27. Production, supply and distribution of goods subject to the provisions of entry 33 of List III.\n\n
    28. Markets and fairs.\n\n
    30. Money-lending and money-lenders; relief of agricultural indebtedness.\n\n
    31. Inns and inn-keepers.\n\n
    32. Incorporation, regulation and winding up of corporations, other than those specified in List I,
    and universities; unincorporated trading, literary, scientific, religious and other societies and
    associations; co-operative societies.\n\n
    33. Theatres and dramatic performances; cinemas subject to the provisions of entry 60 of List I;
    sports, entertainments and amusements.\n\n
    34. Betting and gambling.\n\n
    35. Works, lands and buildings vested in or in the possession of the State.\n\n
    37. Elections to the Legislature of the State subject to the provisions of any law made by
    Parliament.\n\n
    38. Salaries and allowances of members of the Legislature of the State, of the Speaker and
    Deputy Speaker of the Legislative Assembly and, if there is a Legislative Council, of the
    Chairman and Deputy Chairman thereof.\n\n
    39. Powers, privileges and immunities of the Legislative Assembly and of the members and the
    committees thereof, and, if there is a Legislative Council, of that Council and of the members and
    the committees thereof; enforcement of attendance of persons for giving evidence or producing
    documents before committees of the Legislature of the State.\n\n
    40. Salaries and allowances of Ministers for the State.\n\n
    41. State public services; State Public Service Commission.\n\n
    42. State pensions, that is to say, pensions payable by the State or out of the Consolidated Fund
    of the State.\n\n
    43. Public debt of the State.\n\n
    44. Treasure trove.\n\n
    45. Land revenue, including the assessment and collection of revenue, the maintenance of land
    records, survey for revenue purposes and records of rights, and alienation of revenues.\n\n
    46. Taxes on agricultural income.\n\n
    47. Duties in respect of succession to agricultural land.\n\n
    48. Estate duty in respect of agricultural land.\n\n
    49. Taxes on lands and buildings.\n\n
    50. Taxes on mineral rights subject to any limitations imposed by Parliament by law relating to
    mineral development.\n\n
    51. Duties of excise on the following goods manufactured or produced in the State and
    countervailing duties at the same or lower rates on similar goods manufactured or produced
    elsewhere in India:—\n\n
    (a) alcoholic liquors for human consumption;\n\n
    (b) opium, Indian hemp and other narcotic drugs and narcotics,
    but not including medicinal and toilet preparations containing alcohol or any substance included in
    sub-paragraph (b) of this entry.\n\n
    52. Taxes on the entry of goods into a local area for consumption, use or sale therein.\n\n
    53. Taxes on the consumption or sale of electricity.\n\n
    54. Taxes on the sale or purchase of goods other than newspapers, subject to the provisions of
    entry 92A of List I.\n\n
    55. Taxes on advertisements other than advertisements published in the newspapers and
    advertisements broadcast by radio or television.\n\n
    56. Taxes on goods and passengers carried by road or on inland waterways.\n\n
    57. Taxes on vehicles, whether mechanically propelled or not, suitable for use on roads,
    including tramcars subject to the provisions of entry 35 of List III.\n\n
    58. Taxes on animals and boats.\n\n
    59. Tolls.\n\n
    60. Taxes on professions, trades, callings and employments.\n\n
    61. Capitation taxes.\n\n
    62. Taxes on luxuries, including taxes on entertainments, amusements, betting and gambling.\n\n
    63. Rates of stamp duty in respect of documents other than those specified in the provisions of
    List I with regard to rates of stamp duty.\n\n
    64. Offences against laws with respect to any of the matters in this List.\n\n
    65. Jurisdiction and powers of all courts, except the Supreme Court, with respect to any of the
    matters in this List. \n\n
    66. Fees in respect of any of the matters in this List, but not including fees taken in any court. \n\n
<b>List III—Concurrent List</b>\n\n
    1. Criminal law, including all matters included in the Indian Penal Code at the commencement
    of this Constitution but excluding offences against laws with respect to any of the matters
    specified in List I or List II and excluding the use of naval, military or air forces or any other
    armed forces of the Union in aid of the civil power. \n\n
    2. Criminal procedure, including all matters included in the Code of Criminal Procedure at the
    commencement of this Constitution. \n\n
    3. Preventive detention for reasons connected with the security of a State, the maintenance of
    public order, or the maintenance of supplies and services essential to the community; persons
    subjected to such detention. \n\n
    4. Removal from one State to an other State of prisoners, accused persons and persons subjected
    to preventive detention for reasons specified in entry 3 of this List. \n\n
    5. Marriage and divorce; infants and minors; adoption; wills, intestacy and succession; joint
    family and partition; all matters in respect of which parties in judicial proceedings were
    immediately before the commencement of this Constitution subject to their personal law. \n\n
    6. Transfer of property other than agricultural land; registration of deeds and documents. \n\n
    7. Contracts, including partnership, agency, contracts of carriage, and other special forms of
    contracts, but not including contracts relating to agricultural land. \n\n
    8. Actionable wrongs. \n\n
    9. Bankruptcy and insolvency. \n\n
    10. Trust and Trustees. \n\n
    11. Administrators-general and official trustees. \n\n
    11A. Administration of Justice; constitution and organisation of all courts, except the Supreme
    Court and the High Courts. \n\n
    12. Evidence and oaths; recognition of laws, public acts and records, and judicial proceedings. \n\n
    13. Civil procedure, including all matters included in the Code of Civil Procedure at the
    commencement of this Constitution, limitation and arbitration. \n\n
    14. Contempt of court, but not including contempt of the Supreme Court. \n\n
    15. Vagrancy; nomadic and migratory tribes. \n\n
    16. Lunacy and mental deficiency, including places for the reception or treatment of lunatics and
    mental deficients. \n\n
    17. Prevention of cruelty to animals. \n\n
    17A. Forests. \n\n
    17B. Protection of wild animals and birds. \n\n
    18. Adulteration of foodstuffs and other goods. \n\n
    19. Drugs and poisons, subject to the provisions of entry 59 of List I with respect to opium. \n\n
    20. Economic and social planning. \n\n
    20A. Population control and family planning. \n\n
    21. Commercial and industrial monopolies, combines and trusts. \n\n
    22. Trade unions; industrial and labour disputes. \n\n
    23. Social security and social insurance; employment and unemployment. \n\n
    24. Welfare of labour including conditions of work, provident funds, employers\' liability,
    workmen\'s compensation, invalidity and old age pensions and maternity benefits. \n\n
    25. Education, including technical education, medical education and universities, subject to the
    provisions of entries 63, 64, 65 and 66 of List I; vocational and technical training of labour. \n\n
    26. Legal, medical and other professions. \n\n
    27. Relief and rehabilitation of persons displaced from their original place of residence by
    reason of the setting up of the Dominions of India and Pakistan. \n\n
    28. Charities and charitable institutions, charitable and religious endowments and religious
    institutions. \n\n
    29. Prevention of the extension from one State to another of infectious or contagious diseases or
    pests affecting men, animals or plants. \n\n
    30. Vital statistics including registration of births and deaths. \n\n
    31. Ports other than those declared by or under law made by Parliament or existing law to be
    major ports. \n\n
    32. Shipping and navigation on inland waterways as regards mechanically propelled vessels, and
    the rule of the road on such waterways, and the carriage of passengers and goods on inland
    waterways subject to the provisions of List I with respect to national waterways. \n\n
    33. Trade and commerce in, and the production, supply and distribution of,—
    (a) the products of any industry where the control of such industry by the Union
    is declared by Parliament by law to be expedient in the public interest, and
    imported goods of the same kind as such products; \n\n
    (b) foodstuffs, including edible oilseeds and oils; \n\n
    (c) cattle fodder, including oilcakes and other concentrates; \n\n
    (d) raw cotton, whether ginned or unginned, and cotton seed; and\n\n
    (e) raw jute. \n\n
    33A. Weights and measures except establishment of standards. \n\n
    34. Price control. \n\n
    35. Mechanically propelled vehicles including the principles on which taxes on such vehicles are
    to be levied. \n\n
    36. Factories\n\n
    37. Boilers. \n\n
    38. Electricity. \n\n
    39. Newspapers, books and printing presses. \n\n
    40. Archaeological sites and remains other than those declared by or under law made by
    Parliament to be of national importance. \n\n
    41. Custody, management and disposal of property (including agricultural land) declared by law
    to be evacuee property. \n\n
    42. Acquisition and requisitioning of property. \n\n
    43. Recovery in a State of claims in respect of taxes and other public demands, including arrears
    of land-revenue and sums recoverable as such arrears, arising outside that State. \n\n
    44. Stamp duties other than duties or fees collected by means of judicial stamps, but not
    including rates of stamp duty. \n\n
    45. Inquiries and statistics for the purposes of any of the matters specified in
    List II or List III. \n\n
    46. Jurisdiction and powers of all courts, except the Supreme Court, with respect to any of the
    matters in this List. \n\n
    47. Fees in respect of any of the matters in this List, but not including fees taken in any court. \n\n
    </string>
<string name="eighthschedule">
<b>EIGHTH SCHEDULE</b>\n
    [Articles 344 (1) and 351]\n\n
<b>Languages</b>\n\n
    1. Assamese.\n
    2. Bengali.\n
    3. Bodo.\n
    4. Dogri.\n
    5. Gujarati.\n
    6. Hindi.\n
    7. Kannada.\n
    8. Kashmiri.\n
    9. Konkani.\n
    10. Maithili.\n
    11. Malayalam.\n
    12. Manipuri.\n
    13. Marathi.\n
    14. Nepali.\n
    15. Oriya.\n
    16. Punjabi.\n
    17. Sanskrit.\n
    18. Santhali.\n
    19. Sindhi.\n
    20. Tamil.\n
    21. Telugu.\n
    22. Urdu.\n\n
    </string>
    <string name="ninthschedule">
<b>NINTH SCHEDULE</b>\n
    (Article 31B)\n\n
    1. The Bihar Land Reforms Act, 1950 (Bihar Act XXX of 1950)./n/n
    2. The Bombay Tenancy and Agricultural Lands Act, 1948 (Bombay Act LXVII of 1948).\n\n
    3. The Bombay Maleki Tenure Abolition Act, 1949 (Bombay Act LXI of 1949).\n\n
    4. The Bombay Taluqdari Tenure Abolition Act, 1949 (Bombay Act LXII of 1949).\n\n
    5. The Panch Mahals Mehwassi Tenure Abolition Act, 1949 (Bombay Act LXIII of 1949).\n\n
    6. The Bombay Khoti Abolition Act, 1950 (Bombay Act VI of 1950).\n\n
    7. The Bombay Paragana and Kulkarni Watan Abolition Act, 1950 (Bombay Act LX of 1950). \n\n
    8. The Madhya Pradesh Abolition of Proprietary Rights (Estates, Mahals, Alienated Lands) Act,
    1950 (Madhya Pradesh Act I of 1951). \n\n
    9. The Madras Estates (Abolition and Conversion into Ryotwari) Act, 1948 (Madras Act XXVI
    of 1948). \n\n
    10. The Madras Estates (Abolition and Conversion into Ryotwari) Amendment Act, 1950
    (Madras Act I of 1950). \n\n
    11. The Uttar Pradesh Zamindari Abolition and Land Reforms Act, 1950 (Uttar Pradesh Act I
    of 1951). \n\n
    12. The Hyderabad (Abolition of Jagirs) Regulation, 1358F (No. LXIX of 1358, Fasli). \n\n
    13. The Hyderabad Jagirs (Commutation) Regulation, 1359F (No. XXV of 1359, Fasli). \n\n
    14. The Bihar Displaced Persons Rehabilitation (Acquisition of Land) Act, 1950 (Bihar Act
    XXXVIII of 1950). \n\n
    15. The United Provinces Land Acquisition (Rehabilitation of Refugees) Act, 1948 (U.P. Act
    XXVI of 1948). \n\n
    16. The Resettlement of Displaced Persons (Land Acquisition) Act, 1948 (Act LX of 1948). \n\n
    17. Sections 52A to 52G of the Insurance Act, 1938 (Act IV of 1938), as inserted by section 42
    of the Insurance (Amendment) Act, 1950 (Act XLVII of 1950). \n\n
    18. The Railway Companies (Emergency Provisions) Act, 1951 (Act LI of 1951). \n\n
    19. Chapter III-A of the Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 (Act LXV of 1951),
    as inserted by section 13 of the Industries (Development and Regulation) Amendment Act, 1953
    (Act XXVI of 1953). \n\n
    20. The West Bengal Land Development and Planning Act, 1948 (West Bengal Act XXI of
    1948), as amended by West Bengal Act XXIX of 1951. \n\n
    21. The Andhra Pradesh Ceiling on Agricultural Holdings Act, 1961 (Andhra Pradesh Act X of
    1961). \n\n
    22. The Andhra Pradesh (Telangana Area) Tenancy and Agricultural Lands (Validation) Act,
    1961 (Andhra Pradesh Act XXI of 1961). \n\n
    23. The Andhra Pradesh (Telangana Area) Ijara and Kowli Land Cancellation of Irregular
    Pattas and Abolition of Concessional Assessment Act, 1961 (Andhra Pradesh Act XXXVI of
    1961). \n\n
    24. The Assam State Acquisition of Lands belonging to Religious or Charitable Institution of
    Public Nature Act, 1959 (Assam Act IX of 1961). \n\n
    25. The Bihar Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1953 (Bihar Act XX of 1954). \n\n
    26. The Bihar Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling Area and Acquisition of Surplus Land) Act,
    1961 (Bihar Act XII of 1962), except section 28 of this Act. \n\n
    27. The Bombay Taluqdari Tenure Abolition (Amendment) Act, 1954 (Bombay Act I of 1955). \n\n
    28. The Bombay Taluqdari Tenure Abolition (Amendment) Act, 1957 (Bombay Act XVIII of
    1958). \n\n
    29. The Bombay Inams (Kutch Area) Abolition Act, 1958 (Bombay Act XCVIII of 1958). \n\n
    30. The Bombay Tenancy and Agricultural Lands (Gujarat Amendment) Act, 1960 (Gujarat Act
    XVI of 1960). \n\n
    31. The Gujarat Agricultural Lands Ceiling Act, 1960 (Gujarat Act XXVI of 1961). \n\n
    32. The Sagbara and Mehwassi Estates (Proprietary Rights Abolition, etc.) Regulation, 1962
    (Gujarat Regulation I of 1962). \n\n
    33. The Gujarat Surviving Alienations Abolition Act, 1963 (Gujarat Act XXXIII of 1963),
    except in so far as this Act relates to an alienation referred to in sub-clause (d) of clause (3) of
    section 2 thereof. \n\n
    34. The Maharashtra Agricultural Lands (Ceiling on Holdings) Act, 1961 (Maharashtra Act
    XXVII of 1961). \n\n
    35. The Hyderabad Tenancy and Agricultural Lands (Re-enactment, Validation and Further
    Amendment) Act, 1961 (Maharashtra Act XLV of 1961). \n\n
    36. The Hyderabad Tenancy and Agricultural Lands Act, 1950 (Hyderabad Act XXI of 1950). \n\n
    37. The Jenmikaram Payment (Abolition) Act, 1960 (Kerala Act III of 1961). \n\n
    38. The Kerala Land Tax Act, 1961 (Kerala Act XIII of 1961). \n\n
    39. The Kerala Land Reforms Act, 1963 (Kerala Act I of 1964). \n\n
    40. The Madhya Pradesh Land Revenue Code, 1959 (Madhya Pradesh Act XX of 1959). \n\n
    41. The Madhya Pradesh Ceiling on Agricultural Holdings Act, 1960 (Madhya Pradesh Act XX
    of 1960). \n\n
    42. The Madras Cultivating Tenants Protection Act, 1955 (Madras Act XXV of 1955). \n\n
    43. The Madras Cultivating Tenants (Payment of Fair Rent) Act, 1956 (Madras Act XXIV of
    1956). \n\n
    44. The Madras Occupants of Kudiyiruppu (Protection from Eviction) Act, 1961 (Madras Act
    XXXVIII of 1961). \n\n
    45. The Madras Public Trusts (Regulation of Administration of Agricultural Lands) Act, 1961
    (Madras Act LVII of 1961). \n\n
    46. The Madras Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Act, 1961 (Madras Act LVIII of
    1961). \n\n
    47. The Mysore Tenancy Act, 1952 (Mysore Act XIII of 1952). \n\n
    48. The Coorg Tenants Act, 1957 (Mysore Act XIV of 1957). \n\n
    49. The Mysore Village Offices Abolition Act, 1961 (Mysore Act XIV of 1961). \n\n
    50. The Hyderabad Tenancy and Agricultural Lands (Validation) Act, 1961 (Mysore Act
    XXXVI of 1961). \n\n
    51. The Mysore Land Reforms Act, 1961 (Mysore Act X of 1962). \n\n
    52. The Orissa Land Reforms Act, 1960 (Orissa Act XVI of 1960). \n\n
    53. The Orissa Merged Territories (Village Offices Abolition) Act, 1963 (Orissa Act X of 1963). \n\n
    54. The Punjab Security of Land Tenures Act, 1953 (Punjab Act X of 1953). \n\n
    55. The Rajasthan Tenancy Act, 1955 (Rajasthan Act III of 1955). \n\n
    56. The Rajasthan Zamindari and Biswedari Abolition Act, 1959 (Rajasthan Act VIII of 1959). \n\n
    57. The Kumaun and Uttarakhand Zamindari Abolition and Land Reforms Act, 1960 (Uttar
    Pradesh Act XVII of 1960). \n\n
    58. The Uttar Pradesh Imposition of Ceiling on Land Holdings Act, 1960 (Uttar Pradesh Act I of
    1961). \n\n
    59. The West Bengal Estates Acquisition Act, 1953 (West Bengal Act I of 1954). \n\n
    60. The West Bengal Land Reforms Act, 1955 (West Bengal Act X of 1956). \n\n
    61. The Delhi Land Reforms Act, 1954 (Delhi Act VIII of 1954). \n\n
    62. The Delhi Land Holdings (Ceiling) Act, 1960 (Central Act 24 of 1960). \n\n
    63. The Manipur Land Revenue and Land Reforms Act, 1960 (Central Act 33 of 1960). \n\n
    64. The Tripura Land Revenue and Land Reforms Act, 1960 (Central Act 43 of 1960). \n\n
    65. The Kerala Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1969 (Kerala Act 35 of 1969). \n\n
    66. The Kerala Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1971 (Kerala Act 25 of 1971). \n\n
    67. The Andhra Pradesh Land Reforms (Ceiling on Agricultural Holdings) Act, 1973 (Andhra
    Pradesh Act 1 of 1973). \n\n
    68. The Bihar Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling Area and Acquisition of Surplus Land)
    (Amendment) Act, 1972 (Bihar Act 1 of 1973). \n\n
    69. The Bihar Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling Area and Acquisition of Surplus Land)
    (Amendment) Act, 1973 (Bihar Act IX of 1973). \n\n
    70. The Bihar Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1972 (Bihar Act V of 1972). \n\n
    71. The Gujarat Agricultural Lands Ceiling (Amendment) Act, 1972 (Gujarat Act 2 of 1974). \n\n
    72. The Haryana Ceiling on Land Holdings Act, 1972 (Haryana Act 26 of 1972). \n\n
    73. The Himachal Pradesh Ceiling on Land Holdings Act, 1972 (Himachal Pradesh Act 19 of
    1973). \n\n
    74. The Kerala Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1972 (Kerala Act 17 of 1972). \n\n
    75. The Madhya Pradesh Ceiling on Agricultural Holdings (Amendment) Act, 1972 (Madhya
    Pradesh Act 12 of 1974). \n\n
    76. The Madhya Pradesh Ceiling on Agricultural Holdings (Second Amendment) Act, 1972
    (Madhya Pradesh Act 13 of 1974). \n\n
    77. The Mysore Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1973 (Karnataka Act 1 of 1974). \n\n
    78. The Punjab Land Reforms Act, 1972 (Punjab Act 10 of 1973). \n\n
    79. The Rajasthan Imposition of Ceiling on Agricultural Holdings Act, 1973 (Rajasthan Act 11
    of 1973). \n\n
    80. The Gudalur Janmam Estates (Abolition and Conversion into Ryotwari) Act, 1969 (Tamil
    Nadu Act 24 of 1969). \n\n
    81. The West Bengal Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1972 (West Bengal Act XII of 1972). \n\n
    82. The West Bengal Estates Acquisition (Amendment) Act, 1964 (West Bengal Act XXII of
    1964). \n\n
    83. The West Bengal Estates Acquisition (Second Amendment) Act, 1973 (West Bengal Act
    XXXIII of 1973). \n\n
    84. The Bombay Tenancy and Agricultural Lands (Gujarat Amendment) Act, 1972 (Gujarat Act
    5 of 1973). \n\n
    85. The Orissa Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1974 (Orissa Act 9 of 1974). \n\n
    86. The Tripura Land Revenue and Land Reforms (Second Amendment) Act,1974 (Tripura Act
    7 of 1974). \n\n
    88. The Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 (Central Act 65 of 1951). \n\n
    89. The Requisitioning and Acquisition of Immovable Property Act, 1952 (Central Act 30 of
    1952). \n\n
    90. The Mines and Minerals (Regulation and Development) Act, 1957 (Central Act 67 of 1957). \n\n
    91. The Monopolies and Restrictive Trade Practices Act, 1969 (Central Act 54 of 1969). \n\n
    * * * * *
    93. The Coking Coal Mines (Emergency Provisions) Act, 1971 (Central Act 64 of 1971). \n\n
    94. The Coking Coal Mines (Nationalisation) Act, 1972 (Central Act 36 of 1972). \n\n
    95. The General Insurance Business (Nationalisation) Act, 1972 (Central Act 57 of 1972). \n\n
    96. The Indian Copper Corporation (Acquisition of Undertaking) Act, 1972 (Central Act 58 of
    1972). \n\n
    97. The Sick Textile Undertakings (Taking Over of Management) Act, 1972 (Central Act 72 of
    1972). \n\n
    98. The Coal Mines (Taking Over of Management) Act, 1973 (Central Act 15 of 1973). \n\n
    99. The Coal Mines (Nationalisation) Act, 1973 (Central Act 26 of 1973). \n\n
    100. The Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, 1973 (Central Act 46 of 1973). \n\n
    101. The Alcock Ashdown Company Limited (Acquisition of Undertakings) Act, 1973 (Central
    Act 56 of 1973). \n\n
    102. The Coal Mines (Conservation and Development) Act, 1974 (Central Act 28 of 1974). \n\n
    103. The Additional Emoluments (Compulsory Deposit) Act, 1974 (Central Act 37 of 1974). \n\n
    104. The Conservation of Foreign Exchange and Prevention of Smuggling Activities Act, 1974
    (Central Act 52 of 1974). \n\n
    105. The Sick Textile Undertakings (Nationalisation) Act, 1974 (Central Act 57 of 1974). \n\n
    106. The Maharashtra Agricultural Lands (Ceiling on Holdings) (Amendment) Act, 1964
    (Maharashtra Act XVI of 1965). \n\n
    107. The Maharashtra Agricultural Lands (Ceiling on Holdings) (Amendment) Act, 1965
    (Maharashtra Act XXXII of 1965). \n\n
    108. The Maharashtra Agricultural Lands (Ceiling on Holdings) (Amendment) Act, 1968
    (Maharashtra Act XVI of 1968). \n\n
    109. The Maharashtra Agricultural Lands (Ceiling on Holdings) (Second Amendment) Act,
    1968 (Maharashtra Act XXXIII of 1968). \n\n
    110. The Maharashtra Agricultural Lands (Ceiling on Holdings) (Amendment) Act, 1969
    (Maharashtra Act XXXVII of 1969). \n\n
    111. The Maharashtra Agricultural Lands (Ceiling on Holdings) (Second Amendment) Act,
    1969 (Maharashtra Act XXXVIII of 1969). \n\n
    112. The Maharashtra Agricultural Lands (Ceiling on Holdings) (Amendment) Act, 1970
    (Maharashtra Act XXVII of 1970). \n\n
    113. The Maharashtra Agricultural Lands (Ceiling on Holdings) (Amendment) Act, 1972
    (Maharashtra Act XIII of 1972). \n\n
    114. The Maharashtra Agricultural Lands (Ceiling on Holdings) (Amendment) Act, 1973
    (Maharashtra Act L of 1973). \n\n
    115. The Orissa Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1965 (Orissa Act 13 of 1965). \n\n
    116. The Orissa Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1966 (Orissa Act 8 of 1967). \n\n
    117. The Orissa Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1967 (Orissa Act 13 of 1967). \n\n
    118. The Orissa Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1969 (Orissa Act 13 of 1969). \n\n
    119. The Orissa Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1970 (Orissa Act 18 of 1970). \n\n
    120. The Uttar Pradesh Imposition of Ceiling on Land Holdings (Amendment) Act, 1972 (Uttar
    Pradesh Act 18 of 1973). \n\n
    121. The Uttar Pradesh Imposition of Ceiling on Land Holdings (Amendment) Act, 1974 (Uttar
    Pradesh Act 2 of 1975). \n\n
    122. The Tripura Land Revenue and Land Reforms (Third Amendment) Act, 1975 (Tripura Act
    3 of 1975). \n\n
    123.The Dadra and Nagar Haveli Land Reforms Regulation, 1971 (3 of 1971). \n\n
    124. The Dadra and Nagar Haveli Land Reforms (Amendment) Regulation, 1973 (5 of 1973). \n\n
    125. Section 66A and Chapter IVA of the Motor Vehicles Act, 1939 *
    (Central Act 4 of 1939). \n\n
    126. The Essential Commodities Act, 1955 (Central Act 10 of 1955). \n\n
    127. The Smugglers and Foreign Exchange Manipulators (Forfeiture of Property) Act, 1976
    (Central Act 13 of 1976). \n\n
    128. The Bonded Labour System (Abolition) Act, 1976 (Central Act 19 of 1976). \n\n
    129. The Conservation of Foreign Exchange and Prevention of Smuggling Activities
    (Amendment) Act, 1976 (Central Act 20 of 1976). \n\n
    * * * * *
    131. The Levy Sugar Price Equalisation Fund Act, 1976 (Central Act 31 of 1976). \n\n
    132. The Urban Land (Ceiling and Regulation) Act, 1976 (Central Act 33 of 1976). \n\n
    133. The Departmentalisation of Union Accounts (Transfer of Personnel) Act, 1976 (Central Act
    59 of 1976). \n\n
    134. The Assam Fixation of Ceiling on Land Holdings Act, 1956 (Assam Act 1 of 1957).
    135. The Bombay Tenancy and Agricultural Lands (Vidarbha Region) Act, 1958 (Bombay Act
    XCIX of 1958). \n\n
    136. The Gujarat Private Forests (Acquisition) Act, 1972 (Gujarat Act 14 of 1973). \n\n
    137. The Haryana Ceiling on Land Holdings (Amendment) Act, 1976 (Haryana Act 17 of 1976). \n\n
    138. The Himachal Pradesh Tenancy and Land Reforms Act, 1972 (Himachal Pradesh Act 8 of
    1974). \n\n
    139. The Himachal Pradesh Village Common Lands Vesting and Utilization Act, 1974
    (Himachal Pradesh Act 18 of 1974). \n\n
    140. The Karnataka Land Reforms (Second Amendment and Miscellaneous Provisions) Act,
    1974 (Karnataka Act 31 of 1974). \n\n
    141. The Karnataka Land Reforms (Second Amendment) Act, 1976 (Karnataka Act 27 of 1976). \n\n
    142. The Kerala Prevention of Eviction Act, 1966 (Kerala Act 12 of 1966). \n\n
    143. The Thiruppuvaram Payment (Abolition) Act, 1969 (Kerala Act 19 of 1969). \n\n
    144. The Sreepadam Lands Enfranchisement Act, 1969 (Kerala Act 20 of 1969). \n\n
    145. The Sree Pandaravaka Lands (Vesting and Enfranchisement) Act, 1971 (Kerala Act 20 of
    1971). \n\n
    146. The Kerala Private Forests (Vesting and Assignment) Act, 1971 (Kerala Act 26 of 1971). \n\n
    147. The Kerala Agricultural Workers Act, 1974 (Kerala Act 18 of 1974). \n\n
    148. The Kerala Cashew Factories (Acquisition) Act, 1974 (Kerala Act 29 of 1974). \n\n
    149. The Kerala Chitties Act, 1975 (Kerala Act 23 of 1975). \n\n
    150. The Kerala Scheduled Tribes (Restriction on Transfer of Lands and Restoration of
    Alienated Lands) Act, 1975 (Kerala Act 31 of 1975). \n\n
    151. The Kerala Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1976 (Kerala Act 15 of 1976). \n\n
    152. The Kanam Tenancy Abolition Act, 1976 (Kerala Act 16 of 1976). \n\n
    153. The Madhya Pradesh Ceiling on Agricultural Holdings (Amendment) Act, 1974 (Madhya
    Pradesh Act 20 of 1974). \n\n
    154. The Madhya Pradesh Ceiling on Agricultural Holdings (Amendment) Act, 1975 (Madhya
    Pradesh Act 2 of 1976). \n\n
    155. The West Khandesh Mehwassi Estates (Proprietary Rights Abolition, etc.) Regulation,
    1961 (Maharashtra Regulation 1 of 1962). \n\n
    156. The Maharashtra Restoration of Lands to Scheduled Tribes Act, 1974 (Maharashtra Act
    XIV of 1975). \n\n
    157. The Maharashtra Agricultural Lands (Lowering of Ceiling on Holdings) and (Amendment)
    Act, 1972 (Maharashtra Act XXI of 1975). \n\n
    158. The Maharashtra Private Forest (Acquisition) Act, 1975 (Maharashtra Act XXIX of 1975).
    159. The Maharashtra Agricultural Lands (Lowering of Ceiling on Holdings) and (Amendment)
    Amendment Act, 1975 (Maharashtra Act XLVII of 1975). \n\n
    160. The Maharashtra Agricultural Lands (Ceiling on Holdings) (Amendment) Act, 1975
    (Maharashtra Act II of 1976). \n\n
    161. The Orissa Estates Abolition Act, 1951 (Orissa Act I of 1952). \n\n
    162. The Rajasthan Colonisation Act, 1954 (Rajasthan Act XXVII of 1954). \n\n
    163. The Rajasthan Land Reforms and Acquisition of Landowners’ Estates Act, 1963 (Rajasthan
    Act 11 of 1964). \n\n
    164. The Rajasthan Imposition of Ceiling on Agricultural Holdings (Amendment) Act, 1976
    (Rajasthan Act 8 of 1976). \n\n
    165. The Rajasthan Tenancy (Amendment) Act, 1976 (Rajasthan Act 12 of 1976). \n\n
    166. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Reduction of Ceiling on Land) Act, 1970 (Tamil Nadu
    Act 17 of 1970). \n\n
    167. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Amendment Act, 1971
    (Tamil Nadu Act 41 of 1971). \n\n
    168. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Amendment Act, 1972
    (Tamil Nadu Act 10 of 1972). \n\n
    169. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Second Amendment Act,
    1972 (Tamil Nadu Act 20 of 1972). \n\n
    170. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Third Amendment Act, 1972
    (Tamil Nadu Act 37 of 1972). \n\n
    171. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Fourth Amendment Act,
    1972 (Tamil Nadu Act 39 of 1972). \n\n
    172. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Sixth Amendment Act, 1972
    (Tamil Nadu Act 7 of 1974). \n\n
    173. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Fifth Amendment Act, 1972
    (Tamil Nadu Act 10 of 1974). \n\n
    174. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Amendment Act, 1974
    (Tamil Nadu Act 15 of 1974). \n\n
    175. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Third Amendment Act, 1974
    (Tamil Nadu Act 30 of 1974). \n\n
    176. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Second Amendment Act,
    1974 (Tamil Nadu Act 32 of 1974). \n\n
    177. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Amendment Act, 1975
    (Tamil Nadu Act 11 of 1975). \n\n
    178. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Second Amendment Act,
    1975 (Tamil Nadu Act 21 of 1975). \n\n
    179. Amendments made to the Uttar Pradesh Zamindari Abolition and Land Reforms Act, 1950
    (Uttar Pradesh Act I of 1951) by the Uttar Pradesh Land Laws (Amendment) Act, 1971 (Uttar
    Pradesh Act 21 of 1971) and the Uttar Pradesh Land Laws (Amendment) Act, 1974 (Uttar Pradesh
    Act 34 of 1974). \n\n
    180. The Uttar Pradesh Imposition of Ceiling on Land Holdings (Amendment) Act, 1976 (Uttar
    Pradesh Act 20 of 1976). \n\n
    181. The West Bengal Land Reforms (Second Amendment) Act, 1972 (West Bengal Act
    XXVIII of 1972). \n\n
    182. The West Bengal Restoration of Alienated Land Act, 1973 (West Bengal Act XXIII of
    1973). \n\n
    183. The West Bengal Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1974 (West Bengal Act XXXIII of
    1974). \n\n
    184. The West Bengal Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1975 (West Bengal Act XXIII of
    1975). \n\n
    185. The West Bengal Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1976 (West Bengal Act XII of 1976). \n\n
    186. The Delhi Land Holdings (Ceiling) Amendment Act, 1976 (Central Act 15 of 1976). \n\n
    187. The Goa, Daman and Diu Mundkars (Protection from Eviction) Act, 1975 (Goa, Daman
    and Diu Act 1 of 1976). \n\n
    188. The Pondicherry Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Act, 1973 (Pondicherry Act
    9 of 1974). \n\n
    189. The Assam (Temporarily Settled Areas) Tenancy Act, 1971 (Assam Act XXIII of 1971). \n\n
    190. The Assam (Temporarily Settled Areas) Tenancy (Amendment) Act, 1974 (Assam Act
    XVIII of 1974). \n\n
    191. The Bihar Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling Area and Acquisition of Surplus Land)
    (Amendment) Amending Act, 1974 (Bihar Act 13 of 1975). \n\n
    192. The Bihar Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling Area and Acquisition of Surplus Land)
    (Amendment) Act, 1976 (Bihar Act 22 of 1976). \n\n
    193. The Bihar Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling Area and Acquisition of Surplus Land)
    (Amendment) Act, 1978 (Bihar Act VII of 1978). \n\n
    194. The Land Acquisition (Bihar Amendment) Act, 1979 (Bihar Act 2 of 1980). \n\n
    195. The Haryana Ceiling on Land Holdings (Amendment) Act, 1977 (Haryana Act 14 of 1977). \n\n
    196. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Amendment Act, 1978
    (Tamil Nadu Act 25 of 1978). \n\n
    197. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Amendment Act, 1979
    (Tamil Nadu Act 11 of 1979). \n\n
    198. The Uttar Pradesh Zamindari Abolition Laws (Amendment) Act, 1978
    (Uttar Pradesh Act 15 of 1978). \n\n
    199. The West Bengal Restoration of Alienated Land (Amendment) Act, 1978 (West Bengal Act
    XXIV of 1978). \n\n
    200. The West Bengal Restoration of Alienated Land (Amendment) Act, 1980 (West Bengal Act
    LVI of 1980). \n\n
    201. The Goa, Daman and Diu Agricultural Tenancy Act, 1964 (Goa, Daman and Diu Act 7 of
    1964). \n\n
    202. The Goa, Daman and Diu Agricultural Tenancy (Fifth Amendment) Act, 1976 (Goa,
    Daman and Diu Act 17 of 1976). \n\n
    203. The Andhra Pradesh Scheduled Areas Land Transfer Regulation, 1959
    (Andhra Pradesh Regulation 1 of 1959). \n\n
    204. The Andhra Pradesh Scheduled Areas Laws (Extension and Amendment) Regulation, 1963
    (Andhra Pradesh Regulation 2 of 1963). \n\n
    205. The Andhra Pradesh Scheduled Areas Land Transfer (Amendment) Regulation, 1970
    (Andhra Pradesh Regulation 1 of 1970). \n\n
    206. The Andhra Pradesh Scheduled Areas Land Transfer (Amendment) Regulation, 1971
    (Andhra Pradesh Regulation 1 of 1971). \n\n
    207. The Andhra Pradesh Scheduled Areas Land Transfer (Amendment) Regulation, 1978
    (Andhra Pradesh Regulation 1 of 1978). \n\n
    208. The Bihar Tenancy Act, 1885 (Bihar Act 8 of 1885). \n\n
    209. The Chota Nagpur Tenancy Act, 1908 (Bengal Act 6 of 1908) (Chapter VIII—sections 46,
    47, 48, 48A and 49; Chapter X—sections 71, 71A and 71B; and Chapter XVIII—sections 240,
    241 and 242). \n\n
    210. The Santhal Parganas Tenancy (Supplementary Provisions) Act, 1949 (Bihar Act 14 of
    1949) except section 53. \n\n
    211. The Bihar Scheduled Areas Regulation, 1969 (Bihar Regulation 1 of 1969). \n\n
    212. The Bihar Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling Area and Acquisition of Surplus Land)
    (Amendment) Act, 1982 (Bihar Act 55 of 1982). \n\n
    213. The Gujarat Devasthan Inams Abolition Act, 1969 (Gujarat Act 16 of 1969). \n\n
    214. The Gujarat Tenancy Laws (Amendment) Act, 1976 (Gujarat Act 37 of 1976). \n\n
    215. The Gujarat Agricultural Lands Ceiling (Amendment) Act, 1976 (President\'s Act 43 of
    1976). \n\n
    216. The Gujarat Devasthan Inams Abolition (Amendment) Act, 1977 (Gujarat Act 27 of 1977). \n\n
    217. The Gujarat Tenancy Laws (Amendment) Act, 1977 (Gujarat Act 30 of 1977). \n\n
    218. The Bombay Land Revenue (Gujarat Second Amendment) Act, 1980 (Gujarat Act 37 of
    1980). \n\n
    219. The Bombay Land Revenue Code and Land Tenure Abolition Laws (Gujarat Amendment)
    Act, 1982 (Gujarat Act 8 of 1982). \n\n
    220. The Himachal Pradesh Transfer of Land (Regulation) Act, 1968
    (Himachal Pradesh Act 15 of 1969). \n\n
    221. The Himchal Pradesh Transfer of Land (Regulation) (Amendment) Act, 1986 (Himachal
    Pradesh Act 16 of 1986). \n\n
    222. The Karnataka Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes (Prohibition of Transfer of Certain
    Lands) Act, 1978 (Karnataka Act 2 of 1979). \n\n
    223. The Kerala Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1978 (Kerala Act 13 of 1978). \n\n
    224. The Kerala Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1981 (Kerala Act 19 of 1981). \n\n
    225. The Madhya Pradesh Land Revenue Code (Third Amendment) Act, 1976 (Madhya Pradesh
    Act 61 of 1976). \n\n
    226. The Madhya Pradesh Land Revenue Code (Amendment) Act, 1980
    (Madhya Pradesh Act 15 of 1980). \n\n
    227. The Madhya Pradesh Akrishik Jot Uchchatam Seema Adhiniyam, 1981
    (Madhya Pradesh Act 11 of 1981). \n\n
    228. The Madhya Pradesh Ceiling on Agricultural Holdings (Second Amendment) Act, 1976
    (Madhya Pradesh Act 1 of 1984). \n\n
    229. The Madhya Pradesh Ceiling on Agricultural Holdings (Amendment) Act, 1984 (Madhya
    Pradesh Act 14 of 1984). \n\n
    230. The Madhya Pradesh Ceiling on Agricultural Holdings (Amendment) Act, 1989 (Madhya
    Pradesh Act 8 of 1989). \n\n
    231. The Maharashtra Land Revenue Code, 1966 (Maharashtra Act 41 of 1966), sections 36,
    36A and 36B. \n\n
    232. The Maharashtra Land Revenue Code and the Maharashtra Restoration of Lands to
    Scheduled Tribes (Second Amendment) Act, 1976 (Maharashtra Act 30 of 1977). \n\n
    233. The Maharashtra Abolition of Subsisting Proprietary Rights to Mines and Minerals in
    certain Lands Act, 1985 (Maharashtra Act 16 of 1985). \n\n
    234. The Orissa Scheduled Areas Transfer of Immovable Property (by Scheduled Tribes)
    Regulation, 1956 (Orissa Regulation 2 of 1956). \n\n
    235. The Orissa Land Reforms (Second Amendment) Act, 1975 (Orissa Act 29 of 1976). \n\n
    236. The Orissa Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1976 (Orissa Act 30 of 1976). \n\n
    237. The Orissa Land Reforms (Second Amendment) Act, 1976 (Orissa Act 44 of 1976). \n\n
    238. The Rajasthan Colonisation (Amendment) Act, 1984 (Rajasthan Act 12 of 1984). \n\n
    239. The Rajasthan Tenancy (Amendment) Act, 1984 (Rajasthan Act 13 of 1984). \n\n
    240. The Rajasthan Tenancy (Amendment) Act, 1987 (Rajasthan Act 21 of 1987). \n\n
    241. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Second Amendment Act,
    1979 (Tamil Nadu Act 8 of 1980). \n\n
    242. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Amendment Act, 1980
    (Tamil Nadu Act 21 of 1980). \n\n
    243. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Amendment Act, 1981
    (Tamil Nadu Act 59 of 1981). \n\n
    244. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Second Amendment Act,
    1983 (Tamil Nadu Act 2 of 1984). \n\n
    245. The Uttar Pradesh Land Laws (Amendment) Act, 1982 (Uttar Pradesh Act 20 of 1982). \n\n
    246. The West Bengal Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1965 (West Bengal Act 18 of 1965). \n\n
    247. The West Bengal Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1966 (West Bengal Act 11 of 1966). \n\n
    248. The West Bengal Land Reforms (Second Amendment) Act, 1969 (West Bengal Act 23 of
    1969). \n\n
    249. The West Bengal Estate Acquisition (Amendment) Act, 1977 (West Bengal Act 36 of
    1977). \n\n
    250. The West Bengal Land Holding Revenue Act, 1979 (West Bengal Act 44 of 1979). \n\n
    251. The West Bengal Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1980 (West Bengal Act 41 of 1980). \n\n
    252. The West Bengal Land Holding Revenue (Amendment) Act, 1981 (West Bengal Act 33 of
    1981). \n\n
    253. The Calcutta Thikka Tenancy (Acquisition and Regulation) Act, 1981
    (West Bengal Act 37 of 1981). \n\n
    254. The West Bengal Land Holding Revenue (Amendment) Act, 1982
    (West Bengal Act 23 of 1982). \n\n
    255. The Calcutta Thikka Tenancy (Acquisition and Regulation) (Amendment) Act, 1984 (West
    Bengal Act 41 of 1984). \n\n
    256. The Mahe Land Reforms Act, 1968 (Pondicherry Act 1 of 1968). \n\n
    257. The Mahe Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1980 (Pondicherry Act 1 of 1981). \n\n
    257A. The Tamil Nadu Backward Classes, Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes (Reservation
    of Seats in Educational Institutions and of appointments or posts in the Services under the State)
    Act, 1993 (Tamil Nadu Act 45 of 1994). \n\n
    258. The Bihar Privileged Persons Homestead Tenancy Act, 1947 (Bihar Act 4
    of 1948). \n\n
    259. The Bihar Consolidation of Holdings and Prevention of Fragmentation Act, 1956 (Bihar
    Act 22 of 1956). \n\n
    260. The Bihar Consolidation of Holdings and Prevention of Fragmentation (Amendment) Act,
    1970 (Bihar Act 7 of 1970). \n\n
    261. The Bihar Privileged Persons Homestead Tenancy (Amendment) Act, 1970 (Bihar Act 9 of
    1970). \n\n
    262. The Bihar Consolidation of Holdings and Prevention of Fragmentation (Amendment) Act,
    1973 (Bihar Act 27 of 1975). \n\n
    263. The Bihar Consolidation of Holdings and Prevention of Fragmentation (Amendment) Act,
    1981 (Bihar Act 35 of 1982). \n\n
    264. The Bihar Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling Area and Acquisition of Surplus Land)
    (Amendment) Act, 1987 (Bihar Act 21 of 1987). \n\n
    265. The Bihar Privileged Persons Homestead Tenancy (Amendment) Act, 1989 (Bihar Act 11
    of 1989). \n\n
    266. The Bihar Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1989 (Bihar Act 11 of 1990). \n\n
    267. The Karnataka Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes (Prohibition of Transfer of Certain
    Lands) (Amendment) Act, 1984 (Karnataka Act 3 of 1984). \n\n
    268. The Kerala Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1989 (Kerala Act 16 of 1989). \n\n
    269. The Kerala Land Reforms (Second Amendment) Act, 1989 (Kerala Act 2 of 1990). \n\n
    270. The Orissa Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1989 (Orissa Act 9 of 1990). \n\n
    271. The Rajasthan Tenancy (Amendment) Act, 1979 (Rajasthan Act 16 of 1979). \n\n
    272. The Rajasthan Colonisation (Amendment) Act, 1987 (Rajasthan Act 2 of 1987). \n\n
    273. The Rajasthan Colonisation (Amendment) Act, 1989 (Rajasthan Act 12 of 1989).\n\n
    274. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Amendment Act, 1983
    (Tamil Nadu Act 3 of 1984). \n\n
    275. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Amendment Act, 1986
    (Tamil Nadu Act 57 of 1986). \n\n
    276. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Second Amendment Act,
    1987 (Tamil Nadu Act 4 of 1988). \n\n
    277. The Tamil Nadu Land Reforms (Fixation of Ceiling on Land) Amendment (Amendment)
    Act, 1989 (Tamil Nadu Act 30 of 1989). \n\n
    278. The West Bengal Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1981 (West Bengal Act 50 of 1981). \n\n
    279. The West Bengal Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1986 (West Bengal Act 5 of 1986). \n\n
    280. The West Bengal Land Reforms (Second Amendment) Act, 1986 (West Bengal Act 19 of
    1986). \n\n
    281. The West Bengal Land Reforms (Third Amendment) Act, 1986 (West Bengal Act 35 of
    1986). \n\n
    282. The West Bengal Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1989 (West Bengal Act 23 of 1989). \n\n
    283. The West Bengal Land Reforms (Amendment) Act, 1990 (West Bengal Act 24 of 1990). \n\n
    284. The West Bengal Land Reforms Tribunal Act, 1991 (West Bengal Act 12 of 1991). \n\n
    Explanation.—Any acquisition made under the Rajasthan Tenancy Act, 1955 (Rajasthan Act III
    of 1955), in contravention of the second proviso to clause (1) of article 31A shall, to the extent of
    the contravention, be void. \n\n
    </string>

<string name="tenthschedule">
<b>TENTH SCHEDULE</b>\n
    [Articles 102(2) and 191(2)]\n\n
    Provisions as to disqualification on ground of defection\n\n
    1. Interpretation.—In this Schedule, unless the context otherwise requires,— \n\n
    (a) "House" means either House of Parliament or the Legislative Assembly or, as
    the case may be, either House of the Legislature of a State; \n\n
    (b) "legislature party", in relation to a member of a House belonging to any
    political party in accordance with the provisions of paragraph 2 or paragraph 4,
    means the group consisting of all the members of that House for the time being
    belonging to that political party in accordance with the said provisions; \n\n
    (c) "original political party", in relation to a member of a House, means the
    political party to which he belongs for the purposes of sub-paragraph (1) of
    paragraph 2; \n\n
    (d) "paragraph" means a paragraph of this Schedule. \n\n
    2. Disqualification on ground of defection.— \n\n (1) Subject to the provisions of paragraphs 4 and
    5, a member of a House belonging to any political party shall be disqualified for being a member
    of the House—\n\n
    (a) if he has voluntarily given up his membership of such political party; or\n\n
    (b) if he votes or abstains from voting in such House contrary to any direction
    issued by the political party to which he belongs or by any person or authority
    authorised by it in this behalf, without obtaining, in either case, the prior
    permission of such political party, person or authority and such voting or
    abstention has not been condoned by such political party, person or authority
    within fifteen days from the date of such voting or abstention. \n\n
    Explanation.—For the purposes of this sub-paragraph,— \n\n
    (a) an elected member of a House shall be deemed to belong to the political
    party, if any, by which he was set up as a candidate for election as such member; \n\n
    (b) a nominated member of a House shall,— \n\n
    (i) where he is a member of any political party on the date of his nomination as such
    member, be deemed to belong to such political party; \n\n
    (ii) in any other case, be deemed to belong to the political party of which he becomes,
    or, as the case may be, first becomes, a member before the expiry of six months from the
    date on which he takes his seat after complying with the requirements of article 99 or, as the
    case may be, article 188. \n\n
    (2) An elected member of a House who has been elected as such otherwise than as a candidate
    set up by any political party shall be disqualified for being a member of the House if he joins any
    political party after such election. \n\n
    (3) A nominated member of a House shall be disqualified for being a member of the House if he
    joins any political party after the expiry of six months from the date on which he takes his seat
    after complying with the requirements of article 99 or, as the case may be, article 188. \n\n
    (4) Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing provisions of this paragraph, a person
    who, on the commencement of the Constitution (Fifty-second Amendment) Act, 1985, is a
    member of a House (whether elected or nominated as such) shall,— \n\n
    (i) where he was a member of political party immediately before such
    commencement, be deemed, for the purposes of sub-paragraph (1) of this
    paragraph, to have been elected as a member of such House as a candidate set up
    by such political party; \n\n
    (ii) in any other case, be deemed to be an elected member of the House who has
    been elected as such otherwise than as a candidate set up by any political party for
    the purposes of sub-paragraph (2) of this paragraph or, as the case may be, be
    deemed to be a nominated member of the House for the purposes of sub-paragraph
    (3) of this paragraph. \n\n
    * * * * *
    4. Disqualification on ground of defection not to apply in case of merger.— \n\n
    (1) A member of
    a House shall not be disqualified under sub-paragraph (1) of paragraph 2 where his original
    political party merges with another political party and he claims that he and any other members of
    his original political party—\n\n
    (a) have become members of such other political party or, as the case may be, of
    a new political party formed by such merger; or\n\n
    (b) have not accepted the merger and opted to function as a separate group,
    and from the time of such merger, such other political party or new political party or
    group, as the case may be, shall be deemed to be the political party to which he
    belongs for the purposes of sub-paragraph (1) of paragraph 2 and to be his original
    political party for the purposes of this sub-paragraph. \n\n
    (2) For the purposes of sub-paragraph (1) of this paragraph, the merger of the
    original political party of a member of a House shall be deemed to have taken place
    if, and only if, not less than two-thirds of the members of the legislature party
    concerned have agreed to such merger. \n\n
    5. Exemption,— \n\n
    Notwithstanding anything contained in this Schedule, a person
    who has been elected to the office of the Speaker or the Deputy Speaker of the House
    of the People or the Deputy Chairman of the Council of States or the Chairman or
    the Deputy Chairman of the Legislative Council of a State or the Speaker or the
    Deputy Speaker of the Legislative Assembly of a State, shall not be disqualified
    under this Schedule,— \n\n
    (a) if he, by reason of his election to such office, voluntarily gives up the
    membership of the political party to which he belonged immediately before such
    election and does not, so long as he continues to hold such office thereafter, rejoin
    that political party or become a member of another political party; or\n\n
    (b) if he, having given up by reason of his election to such office his
    membership of the political party to which he belonged immediately before such
    election, rejoins such political party after he ceases to hold such office. \n\n
    6. Decision on questions as to disqualification on ground of defection.— \n\n
    (1) If
    any question arises as to whether a member of a House has become subject to
    disqualification under this Schedule, the question shall be referred for the decision
    of the Chairman or, as the case may be, the Speaker of such House and his decision
    shall be final: \n\n
    Provided that where the question which has arisen is as to whether the Chairman or the Speaker
    of a House has become subject to such disqualification, the question shall be referred for the
    decision of such member of the House as the House may elect in this behalf and his decision shall
    be final. \n\n
    (2) All proceedings under sub-paragraph (1) of this paragraph in relation to any question as to
    disqualification of a member of a House under this Schedule shall be deemed to be proceedings in
    Parliament within the meaning of article 122 or, as the case may be, proceedings in the Legislature
    of a State within the meaning of article 212. \n\n
    7. Bar of jurisdiction of courts.— \n\n
    Notwithstanding anything in this Constitution, no court
    shall have any jurisdiction in respect of any matter connected with the disqualification of a
    member of a House under this Schedule. \n\n
    8. Rules.— \n\n
    (1) Subject to the provisions of sub-paragraph (2) of this paragraph, the Chairman or
    the Speaker of a House may make rules for giving effect to the provisions of this Schedule, and in
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing, such rules may provide for—\n\n
    (a) the maintenance of registers or other records as to the political parties, if
    any, to which different members of the House belong; \n\n
    (b) the report which the leader of a legislature party in relation to a member of a
    House shall furnish with regard to any condonation of the nature referred to in
    clause (b) of sub-paragraph (1) of paragraph 2 in respect of such member, the time
    within which and the authority to whom such report shall be furnished; \n\n
    (c) the reports which a political party shall furnish with regard to admission to
    such political party of any members of the House and the officer of the House to
    whom such reports shall be furnished; and\n\n
    (d) the procedure for deciding any question referred to in sub-paragraph (1) of
    paragraph 6 including the procedure for any inquiry which may be made for the
    purpose of deciding such question. \n\n
    (2) The rules made by the Chairman or the Speaker of a House under sub-paragraph (1) of this
    paragraph shall be laid as soon as may be after they are made before the House for a total period of
    thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions and shall
    take effect upon the expiry of the said period of thirty days unless they are sooner approved with
    or without modifications or disapproved by the House and where they are so approved, they shall
    take effect on such approval in the form in which they were laid or in such modified form, as the
    case may be, and where they are so disapproved, they shall be of no effect. \n\n
    (3) The Chairman or the Speaker of a House may, without prejudice to the provisions of article
    105 or, as the case may be, article 194, and to any other power which he may have under this
    Constitution direct that any wilful contravention by any person of the rules made under this
    paragraph may be dealt with in the same manner as a breach of privilege of the House. \n\n
    </string>


<string name="eleventhschedule">
<b>ELEVENTH SCHEDULE</b>\n
    (Article 243G)\n\n
    1. Agriculture, including agricultural extension. \n\n
    2. Land improvement, implementation of land reforms, land consolidation and soil
    conservation. \n\n
    3. Minor irrigation, water management and watershed development. \n\n
    4. Animal husbandry, dairying and poultry. \n\n
    5. Fisheries. \n\n
    6. Social forestry and farm forestry. \n\n
    7. Minor forest produce. \n\n
    8. Small scale industries, including food processing industries. \n\n
    9. Khadi, village and cottage industries. \n\n
    10. Rural housing. \n\n
    11. Drinking water. \n\n
    12. Fuel and fodder. \n\n
    13. Roads, culverts, bridges, ferries, waterways and other means of communication. \n\n
    14. Rural electrification, including distribution of electricity. \n\n
    15. Non-conventional energy sources. \n\n
    16. Poverty alleviation programme. \n\n
    17. Education, including primary and secondary schools. \n\n
    18. Technical training and vocational education. \n\n
    19. Adult and non-formal education. \n\n
    20. Libraries. \n\n
    21. Cultural activities. \n\n
    22. Markets and fairs. \n\n
    23. Health and sanitation, including hospitals, primary health centres and dispensaries. \n\n
    24. Family welfare. \n\n
    25. Women and child development. \n\n
    26. Social welfare, including welfare of the handicapped and mentally retarded. \n\n
    27. Welfare of the weaker sections, and in particular, of the Scheduled Castes and the
    Scheduled Tribes. \n\n
    28. Public distribution system. \n\n
    29. Maintenance of community assets. \n\n
    </string>

<string name="twelvethschedule">
<b>TWELVETH SCHEDULE</b>\n
    (Article 243W)\n\n
    1. Urban planning including town planning. \n\n
    2. Regulation of land-use and construction of buildings. \n\n
    3. Planning for economic and social development. \n\n
    4. Roads and bridges. \n\n
    5. Water supply for domestic, industrial and commercial purposes. \n\n
    6. Public health, sanitation conservancy and solid waste management. \n\n
    7. Fire services. \n\n
    8. Urban forestry, protection of the environment and promotion of ecological aspects. \n\n
    9. Safeguarding the interests of weaker sections of society, including the handicapped and
    mentally retarded. \n\n
    10. Slum improvement and upgradation. \n\n
    11. Urban poverty alleviation. \n\n
    12. Provision of urban amenities and facilities such as parks, gardens, playgrounds. \n\n
    13. Promotion of cultural, educational and aesthetic aspects. \n\n
    14. Burials and burial grounds; cremations, cremation grounds; and electric crematoriums. \n\n
    15. Cattle pounds; prevention of cruelty to animals. \n\n
    16. Vital statistics including registration of births and deaths. \n\n
    17. Public amenities including street lighting, parking lots, bus stops and public
    conveniences. \n\n
    18. Regulation of slaughter houses and tanneries.\n\n
    </string>






    </resources>
